<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Misericordiam volo, or, The pharisees lesson shewing the impiety and vnreasonableness of contending for outward formes and ceremonies, to the violation of obedience, charity, and the publick peace.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12787619</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12787619</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51000)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 699:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Misericordiam volo, or, The pharisees lesson shewing the impiety and vnreasonableness of contending for outward formes and ceremonies, to the violation of obedience, charity, and the publick peace.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707. Character of a separatist, or, Sensuality the ground of separation.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also appears as second part of Thomas Long's The character of a separatist, or, Sensuality the ground of separation. ... London, 1677. cf. NUC pre-1956, v. 340, pg. 130.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93904:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MISERICORDIAM VOLO:</hi> OR, THE Phariſees LESSON.
<hi>SHEWING</hi> The <hi>Impiety</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs</hi> of
contending for outward Formes and Ceremonies, to the Violation of Obedience,
Charity, and the Publick Peace.</p>
            <q>Haud dubitem affirmare eos qui falluntur &amp; tamen fraternam
communionem cum aliis retinere parati ſunt, eſſe coram Deo magis
excuſatos, quàm qui veras opiniones in iis controverſiis tuentur,
&amp; mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam communionem cum aliis Eccleſiis etiam deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derantibus,
aſpernantur. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>Davenant.</hi> pro pace Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, <hi>p.
24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the
<hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:93904:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93904:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE <hi>Concerning the Ceremonies</hi> of the
<hi>Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is granted by all ſober Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that the Church hath
po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of making Canons and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, for Decency and Order in the
publick worſhip of God; and not only to preſcribe the neceſſary
circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of time and place; but alſo to continue and eſtabliſh
thoſe ancient rites of the Chriſtian Church, which were practiſed in the
primitive times, and are in themſelves of an indifferent nature; which
authority of the Church was aſſerted in the <hi>Auguſtan</hi>
confeſſion, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. S. 27.
See <hi>T. C. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 27.</note> and particularly by Mr.
<hi>Calvin,</hi> and other worthy perſons in the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which our
Reformers alſo did aſſume to themſelves, as is declared in the 20th.
Article; and hath been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed <pb facs="tcp:93904:3"/>and defended againſt all
Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 
<note place="margin">Acts 15.28. 1 Corinth. 11.16.</note> as well by
Scripture, as by Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and right reaſon: and therefore thoſe
perſons that condemn the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church, which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and
Confeſſors of our Church, did eſtabliſh upon mature deliberation, do
reflect too ſeverely upon thoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, who with equal prudence and
conſtancy, did commend them to us. And the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> was ſo
tender of their reputation, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exact col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. p.</hi> 26.</note> that in
his anſwer to the <hi>Parliaments Remonſtrance,</hi> he promiſeth to
reform the Ceremonies with theſe cautions. 1. That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation were
purſued with ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and ſubmiſſion, that the quiet of the
Kingdom were not diſturbed: 2. Nor the decency and comelineſs of God's
ſervice diſcountenanced: 3. Nor the pious, ſober, and devout actions of
thoſe reverend perſons, who were the firſt labourers in the bleſſed
Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be ſcandalized and defamed. And ſome that are not friends to
Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Saints care for Church Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> p.
334.</note> have vindicated thoſe perſons in this reſpect. 
<q rend="margQuotes">What ſhall we ſay of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<hi>Ridley,</hi> (ſaith Maſter <hi>Crofton</hi>) hearty <hi>Hooper,</hi>
ſincere <hi>Sanders,</hi> truſty <pb facs="tcp:93904:3"/>
                  <hi>Tayler,</hi> and moſt
brave <hi>Bradford,</hi> with the cloud of Witneſſes that ſerved God by
the Liturgy to their laſt breath, even in their moſt perſonal and dying
devotions, and ſuffered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for ſo doing, having the ſame ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
againſt them by their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and alſo preſſed the people, and
their choiceſt friends, to adhere to it, and ſerve God by it. And however
ſome ſucceeding Chriſtians have deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome reformation of the
Liturgy, they have conſtantly, and with due devotion ſerved God in the
uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and defended the ſame againſt the <hi>cenſorious
Browniſts,</hi> and rigid <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts.</hi>
               </q>— And the firſt
reformation had the perfection of ſubſtance, though not of degrees, Gods
true worſhip was reſtored to a right order of miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the
Ordinances of God did then truly exiſt, as to their ſubſtance, and
ſalvably as to their Miniſterial mode towards the people; otherwiſe
thoſe holy Men had not wherein to rejoyce before God and the World. And
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they did not entayl a Popiſh, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, or Idolatrous Yoke
(as ſome call the Ceremonies) on the <pb facs="tcp:93904:4"/>Church of God. Mr.
<hi>Cartwright</hi> was one of the firſt Oppoſers of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and
inſtead of acquainting you with the Anſwers of Arch-Biſhop
<hi>Whitgift,</hi> and judicious <hi>Hooker,</hi> to his arguments, it will be
ſufficient to ſay, that Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> himſelf hath ſaid
enough to confute the diſſenters of our times, for firſt he oppoſed
them, only as inconvenient, not unlawful: and perſwaded Miniſters rather to
wear the Garments than ceaſe their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, 
<note place="margin">2d. <hi>Reply. p.</hi> 262.</note> and in his
<hi>Evangelical Harmony,</hi> on <hi>Luke</hi> 22. (<hi>à</hi> v. 14.
<hi>ad</hi> 19.) he ſaith, that kneeling in the receiving of the Sacrament
being incommodious in its own nature, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 877. <hi>Edit. ult.</hi>
               </note> and
made more incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious by <hi>Popiſh</hi> Superſtition, is not ſo to be
rejected, that for the ſake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we ſhould abſtain from the
Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe the thing is not in its own nature unlawful — And
what his judgment was in the caſe of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, appears in a Letter of his
to Mr. <hi>Harriſon</hi> lately publiſhed: And in another Letter to his
Siſter <hi>Anne Stubs,</hi> reproving her for ſtumbling at this ſtone,
that becauſe of ſome defects in a Church, inſtead of concluding that 
<pb facs="tcp:93904:4"/>Church to be imperfect, ſhe concluded it to be no Church. The
wiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mr. <hi>Hilderſham, Bradſhaw, Paget, Ball, Gifford,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cure of Diviſions. p.</hi> 188.</note> and
other learned Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts of old did foreſee and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear this
Spirit (ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>) But this Spirit being very troubleſome
and pragmatical, the moſt learned of the diſſenters did alway endeavour
to moderate it, as well by their quiet and peaceable practice, as by their
learned and earneſt arguments, and exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to unity in the publick
Worſhip. And accordingly when King <hi>James,</hi> ſhortly after his entry
into the Throne, had appointed the conference at <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton</hi> Court, where
Doctor <hi>Raynolds,</hi> Dr. <hi>Chaderton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Spark,</hi> and
others were appointed to diſcourſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in controverſie, with
ſome <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Divines:</hi> They were ſo far from affirming the
ceremonies to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that they would not have it known that any of that
party were ſo weak, as to affirm it; and Dr. <hi>Raynolds</hi> was ſo far
ſatisfied, that before his death he ſolemnly declared himſelf to be of
the communion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and deſired
abſolution according to the <pb facs="tcp:93904:5"/>form appointed in the Liturgy. About
this time Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> Doctor <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Sprint,</hi> and others did moſt rationally, and irrefragably aſſert
the innocency of the Ceremonies, and the neceſſity of the Miniſters
conforming rather than to ſuffer deprivation, and of the peoples, rather than
to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the Ordinances of Chriſt. I intend not a Hiſtory of the
tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this buſineſs, and therefore ſhall only give you a
brief account of it, from the beginning of our unhappy troubles. The <hi>Long
Parliament</hi> in their Petition, and <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> joyned with it,
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 15. 1642. inform us of ſome Malignant parties, whoſe
proceedings evidently appeared to be, mainly, for the advantage and increaſe
of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and were compoſed, ſet up, and acted, by the ſubtle practice
of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and other Engineers and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for <hi>Rome,</hi>
who had ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, as to corrupt divers of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and others,
in prime places of the Church, 
<note place="margin">Exact Collect.</note> and <hi>p.</hi> 20. they
intimate, that Idolatry, and Popiſh Ceremonies were introduced to the Church,
by command of the Biſhops; and the <pb facs="tcp:93904:5"/>people were not only debarred
the Church, but expelled the Kingdom. And that thoſe were counted fitteſt
for Eccleſiaſtical preferment, and ſooneſt attained it, who were moſt
officious in promoting Superſtition, moſt viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in railing againſt
Godlineſs and honeſty. We deſire (ſay they) to unburthen the
Conſciences of men, of needleſs and Superſtitious Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
ſuppreſs Innovations, and take away the monuments of Idolatry. To this His
Majeſty of Bleſſed Memory anſwered thus. 
<q rend="margQuotes">The fears for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, may haply be,
not only as it may be innovated by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party, but as it is
accompanied with ſome Ceremonies, at which ſome tender Conſciences really
are, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be ſcandalized. Concerning Religion, as there may be any
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of favour, or inclination to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> we are
willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to all the World, that as we have been from our childhood
brought up in, and practiſed the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion now eſtabliſhed, ſo it is
well known, we have (not contented ſimply with the principles of our 
<pb facs="tcp:93904:6"/>Education) given a good proportion of our time and pains, to the
exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the grounds of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as it is different from that of
<hi>Rome,</hi> and are from our Soul ſo fully ſatisfied, and aſſured
that it is the moſt pure, and agreeable to the Sacred Word of God, of any
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion now practiſed in the Chriſtian world, that as we believe we can
maintain the ſame by unanſwerable Reaſons, ſo we hope we ſhould
readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeal to it by the effuſion of our Bloud, if it pleaſed God to
call us to that Sacrifice. And therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſo acceptable to us,
as any propoſition which may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the advancement of it here, or
the propagation of it abroad, being the only means of drawing down the
Bleſſings of God upon our ſelves and this Nation. And we have been
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly unfortunate if this Profeſſion of ours be wanting to our
people— For differences among our ſelves, for matters indifferent in
their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we ſhall, in tenderneſs to any number of our loving
Subjects, very willingly comply with the advice of <pb facs="tcp:93904:6"/>our Parliament,
that ſome Law may be made, for the exemption of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences from
puniſhment, or perſecution, for ſuch Ceremonies, and in ſuch caſes,
which by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of moſt men are held to be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters indifferent, and
of ſome to be abſolutely unlawful. (Provided <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before
mentioned, under the three cautions.) To that clauſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
corruptions (as you ſtile them) in Religion, in Church Government, and in
Diſcipline, and the removing ſuch unneceſſary Ceremonies, as weak
Conſciences might check at: That for any illegal Innovations which may have
crept in, we ſhall willingly concur in the removal of them, but we are very
ſorry to hear in ſuch general terms, corruption in Religion objected,
ſince we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in Conſcience, that no Church on Earth can be
found, that profeſſeth the true Religion with more purity of Doctrine, than
the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth, nor where the Government and Diſcipline
are joyntly more beautified and free from Superſtition, than as they are 
<pb facs="tcp:93904:7"/>here eſtabliſhed by Law, which by the Grace of God we will with
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy maintain, while we live, in their purity and glory, not only
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all invaſions of <hi>Popery,</hi> but alſo from the irreverence
of thoſe Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Separatiſts, wherewith of late this Kingdom
and City abound, to the great diſhonour and hazard of Church and State.</q>
Doubtleſs they had very much of the nature of the <hi>Adder</hi> in them, who
inſtead of being charmed into a quiet and meek ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion by theſe
moſt pious, gracious, ſincere Reaſons and condeſcenſions, did
precipitate themſelves, and the three Nations to thoſe horrible
confuſions, which that Prophetick, as well as Royal Spirit foretold, for
immediately after, the people of the Land being frighted by frequent
remonſtrances of fears and jealouſies of Popery and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, run
themſelves into cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſnares as to their Eſtates, by the inſatiable
oppreſſion of their new Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and their Lives, by their want of
Loyalty, and as to their Conſciences by illegal Oaths and Covenants, till the
beauty of Religion was deſtroyed <pb facs="tcp:93904:7"/>for want of Order and Reverence,
and the ſubſtance of it devoured by Sects and Hereſies of all kinds. And
this moſtly for Reformation of Ceremonies, for the Doctrine needed it not. I
do even tremble to relate in a corner, what a Preacher who was then of great
repute, ſpake in the moſt eminent meeting of the Nation (the preſent
Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1656.) in theſe words. Worthy Patriots, you that
are Rulers, in this preſent Parliament— Praiſed be God, who hath
delivered us from Prelatical innovations, Altar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genu-flexions and cringings,
with croſſings, and all that Popiſh traſh, and trumpery; and truly, I
ſpeak no more, than what I have often thought, and ſaid—The removal
of theſe inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable burdens, countervails for the Bloud and Treaſure
ſhed and ſpent in theſe late diſtractions; nor did I as yet ever hear
of any godly men, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired (were it poſſible) to purchaſe their
friends, or mony again, at ſo dear a rate, as the return of theſe, to have
thoſe Soul-burthening Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian yokes impoſed upon us; if any ſuch
here be, I am ſure, that deſire is <pb facs="tcp:93904:8"/>no part of their
godlineſs, and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my ſelf in that, to be none of the number.] Can
any that bears the name of a Chriſtian hear ſuch things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hornor,
eſpecially when he ſhall ſeriouſly conſider what a deluge of bloud
had overflown the land, The King being Murthered about Eight years before, and
the Sword, and the Axe having glutted themſelves with the Bloud of many Noble
Heroes, and learned Clergy-men? And beſides the many thouſands that dyed
for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Loyalty, there were very many that periſhed alſo
in Rebellion, againſt God and the King. He had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle charity for his
Brethren, that would not on ſuch eaſie conditions, redeem them from the
grave and hell; if we may argue from a Parable, <hi>Dives</hi> had more charity
in that place of Torment, than was in this Preachers breaſt, and if this be a
mark of godlineſs, <hi>Satan</hi> needs not to be transformed, to paſs for
an Angel of light, ſure I am no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more oppoſite to this
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical truth, which the Text that is before us commends, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring mercy before Sacrifice. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend <pb facs="tcp:93904:8"/>it therefore to
your ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, whether thoſe perſons, who ſo
pertinaciouſly inſiſt upon the aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of our Ceremonies, as to
increaſe our diviſions, and engage us again in Bloud and confuſion, are
not acted by a like Spirit of perverſeneſs, that delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf to
live in the fire of contention takes pleaſure in drawing others and
tormenting them in the like flames.</p>
            <p>At the happy return of our Dear Soveraign, who after the example
of his Martyred Father, was careful to ſee the Church eſtabliſhed in its
beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we found this evil Spirit ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to oppoſe as if it had
taken ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven worſe than it ſelf, to ſecure the poſſeſſion which
it had in the hearts of the people, being in danger of being caſt out: then
was <hi>Nehuſtan</hi> ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to perſwade the people, that the
<hi>Liturgy, Ceremonies, and other things uſed in the Church of England,
ought not to be impoſed, nor retained, but utterly extirpated, and laid
aſide, and that every one in his place ought to do his part to the
aboliſhing of it, and not ſit ſtill in the midſt of ſuch defilements
and ſnares, but diſcover their hatred of them, decline <pb facs="tcp:93904:9"/>their
uſe, and endeavour the rooting of them out;</hi> and all upon this ground,
that things which have been abuſed in falſe Worſhip muſt be laid
aſide. 
<note place="margin">Gilaſpy.</note> Then comes another
<hi>Boreas</hi> from the <hi>North</hi> (whence moſt of our evils came)
cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Diſpute againſt the <hi>Engliſh Popiſh Ceremonies,</hi> which
he explains to be, a contending for the purity of Chriſt, againſt the
corruptions of Anti-chriſt, and this Spirit, as if he were indeed of the
triumphant party, leads in chains no meaner perſons, than <hi>Hooker,
Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Burges, Sprint, Paybody, Andrews, Saravia, Tilen, Spotſwood,
Lindſey, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes,</hi> &amp;c. who were all particularly confuted, and
vanquiſhed by him, as he boaſted. But this pitiful man dealt very
mercifully with them, for their chains were ſuch as fell off of their own
accord: and ſo do thoſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous appellations which he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to fix
on the Church, and her practiſes, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Preface, p.</hi> 6.</note> calling them
Popiſh, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, Idle and Idolized, for thus he beſpeaks the
Church of <hi>Scotland:</hi> Oh thou faireſt among Women, what haſt thou to
do with the inveag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling appurtenances and habiliments <pb facs="tcp:93904:9"/>of
<hi>Babylon</hi> the whore <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are as impotent
as his Obloquy, the naming of which is confutation enough, at leaſt, if the
Reader will but turn his negatives into affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and his affirmatives
into nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, the weakneſs of the man, and his manner of arguing will be
mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all.</p>
            <p>As Firſt, when he ſays we are not to account the Ceremonies
matters of ſmall importance] contrary to the ſenſe of ours, and all the
Reformed Churches which account them things indifferent and not worth the
contending for. Secondly, Let not (ſays he) the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of peace and unity
cool your fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or make you ſpare to oppoſe your ſelves to thoſe
idle and Idolized Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies] contrary to the Text, and to <hi>Rom.</hi>
14.17. Thirdly, beware alſo you be not deceived with a pretence of the
Churches conſent, and of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as well with the ancient Church as with
the now Reformed Churches in the forms and cuſtoms of both] as if the
conſent of the Ancient Church before Popery, and all the Reformed ſince,
were one of the ſnares to be <pb facs="tcp:93904:10"/>avoided. Fourthly, moreover,
becauſe the foredeck and hindeck of all our oppoſites probations, do
reſolve and reſt finally into the authority of a law— therefore we
certiorate you with <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> that <hi>Si acquieviſtis imperio,
peſſimo laqueo vos induiſtis</hi>] as if there were no difference between
the eſtabliſhing of iniquity by a Law (of which <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> ſpeaks)
and the laws of our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors for— decency and order. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, do not
reckon it enough to bear within the incloſure of your ſecret thoughts, a
certain diſlike of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contrary to S.</hi> Paul, Ro. 14.22</note>
and other abuſes now ſet on foot; except by profeſſion and action you
evidence the ſame, and ſo ſhew your Faith by your fact: principally
prayers and ſupplications are the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our Spiritual warfare, but as
they ought to be done, ſo the atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other ſecundary means, ought
not to be left undone. Theſe are the chief of his arguments, which he ſums
up in the Epiſtle dedicated to all and every one in the Reformed Churches of
<hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and you may judge by theſe,
of the validity of the whole Book which <pb facs="tcp:93904:10"/>conſiſts of 336.
pages, wherein is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing objected, or aſſerted, but what hath been
abundantly confuted by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent reaſons and arguments. After this
<hi>Scottiſh</hi> Pipe march many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formado's headed by
Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> whoſe chief objection is, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal love. p.</hi> 212.</note> that
the ceremonies are unwritten and unſcriptural inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men, and that
<hi>Chriſt</hi>'s war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and authority muſt be ſhewn, for what is
impoſed in the worſhip of God. The ridiculouſneſs of this objection
hath been clearly demonſtrated by the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon;</hi>
and others. Then Mr. <hi>Hickman</hi> ſends forth his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, and his
<hi>Bonaſus Vapulans,</hi> who inveighs againſt the ceremonies,
eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for being ſignificant, and inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the ſign of the
Croſs, which is made a ſign of dedication to God, in Token that
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas others of his party do oppoſe them, becauſe they
are not ſignificative enough.</p>
            <p>To him ſucceeds the Author of the <hi>Reherſal,</hi> who
ſays that the Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts defining a Sacrament to be an outward and
viſible ſign of an inward and ſpiritual grace (Omitting the chief part of
the definition [<hi>viz.</hi> ordained <pb facs="tcp:93904:11"/>by <hi>Chriſt</hi>
himſelf]) do make the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of a Sacramental nature. To theſe the
learned <hi>Ritchel</hi> in his Tract <hi>de Ceremoniis,</hi> gives
ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to all unprejudiced Readers, and <hi>Durel,
Parker</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> &amp; Mr.
<hi>Baxter</hi> have done the ſame. 41.61. p. 90, 454.</note>, and others
have done no leſs. It will be but labour in vain, to repeat here all the
ſolid replies to thoſe empty objections. One ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument from
Scripture, as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our urgeth in the Text, againſt thoſe that on
pretence of contending for their own, againſt the eſtabliſhed rites and
cuſtomes of the Church, do vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the laws of Obedience, Love, and Peace,
will ſilence them all, if they be not poſſeſt with a ſpirit of
contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For if we ſhould ſuppoſe that the rites and ceremonies
were as expreſly ſet down in the Goſpel to be uſed, or forborn in the
publick worſhip of God, as the rites and circumſtances concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Sacrifices, were in the ceremonial law: yet as the Sacrifices themſelves,
much more the modes of preparing and offering them, might be uſed or omitted,
for the performance of moral duties; ſo doubtleſs, if things of an
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, ceremonial nature, had been <pb facs="tcp:93904:11"/>commanded, or forbidden in
expreſs terms, they might yet be obſerved, or omitted, as the
ſubſtantial ſervice of God, and obedience to his greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, for
charity and peace might be beſt performed. But theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not
determined particularly by the Goſpel, but left under general rules, for
decency and order, may doubtleſs be determined by a lawful authority, ſuch
as that of our Church, under our Gracious Soveraign, is, and being ſo
determined and impoſed, there is an advantage on the ſide of Authority,
againſt a ſcrupulous conſcience, which ought to over rule the practice of
ſuch who are members of that Church. It remains only that I endeavour to
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move an objection or two againſt what is here ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. If the ceremonies be things of ſuch
indifferency, Why do not they who are in authority, diſpenſe with the uſe
of them, or totally lay them aſide for the ſake of peace and unity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Magiſtrate doth but his duty in
providing for the ſolemnity of Divine worſhip, according to thoſe general
rules for decency and order <pb facs="tcp:93904:12"/>preſcribed by the Apoſtles.
2<hi>ly,</hi> What the Magiſtrate doth, is not only agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his private
diſcretion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, (for he practiſeth the ſame things that he
preſcribes) but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the deliberate determinations of the moſt
wiſe and pious perſons of the Nation, in their ſolemn Aſſemblies, and
doubtleſs (as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> wrote to St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) if
they had known any thing better, they would have practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that.
3<hi>ly,</hi> It will very much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the authority and reputation of
Magiſtrates, ſo to comply with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune clamours of ſcrupulous
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as to alter or abrogate their laws and conſtitutions, as oft as
diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſeduced perſons ſhall demand it. And though it be very
uncertain that the craving party will be ſatisfied, when they are indulged in
all that they deſire, yet it is certain that others will be incouraged to
make new ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, and ſo create perpetual di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances. And the
gratifying of a few weaklings, or male-contents, may give juſt cauſe of
offence, to a greater and better party, who are deſirous to worſhip God in
the beauty of holineſs, <pb facs="tcp:93904:12"/>and are really grieved at the
irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and diſorders which are, and have been too obſervable in the
Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of diſſenting parties. 4<hi>ly,</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Magiſtrate
ſhould tacitly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs himſelf guilty of all thoſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that
have been charged upon him, and his predeceſſors, of impoſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,
ſuperſtitious and <hi>Popiſh</hi> cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and perſecuting the
godly and conſcientious people, that could not conform to them. And
5<hi>ly,</hi> It would greatly defame thoſe worthy Martyrs, who not only
thought fit to retain them, and gave cogent arguments for the lawful uſe of
them, but ſealed the eſtabliſhed worſhip and diſcipline with their
bloud, not only in the <hi>Marian</hi> days, but under the late Uſurpation
alſo. 6<hi>ly,</hi> It is an unreaſonable thing, to demand that, which they
themſelves would deny, if they were in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates place; for let me
ask them, whether they, being well perſwaded of their diſcipline and order
(<hi>viz.</hi> that it is agreeable to the Word of God, to antiquity and
reaſon) would comply with the deſires of diſſenting parties, to make
ſuch alterations, as ſhould from <pb facs="tcp:93904:13"/>time to time be required by
others, contrary to their own judgments and conſciences? and to this we need
no other anſwer, than the practice of the Objectors, when they were in
Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And who can doubt, but that they, who being ſubjects, do
aſſume to themſelves a power of directing and preſcribing to the
Magiſtrate, if they were in the Magiſtrates place would take it very ill to
be directed by their Subjects. 7<hi>ly,</hi> If the eſtabliſhed cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
were removed, others of a like nature would ſucceed, as unſcriptural, and
ſymbolical as they, (ſuch as ſitting at the Sacrament, and lifting up the
hands to Heaven,) it being impoſſible almoſt to perform divine ſervice,
with any decency, without ſuch: and ſeeing that for many centuries of the
Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, wherein other ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies have been complained of by Saint
<hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and others, no man ever objected againſt the ceremonies
which are uſed in our Church, and which were by thoſe famous Reformers and
Martyrs retained in our Liturgy, it is no argument of a meek or quiet ſpirit,
to make objections, and cauſe diviſions <pb facs="tcp:93904:13"/>upon pretence of
Superſtition in the Liturgy and ceremonies, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that the Church to
ſalve their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation ſhould betray her own, and by abrogating her
ſanctions, give the world more reaſon than yet hath been given, to believe,
that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> even from the firſt Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath
been in a dangerous error, and the Factions that oppoſed her, have had truth
and juſtice on their ſide.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Objection, Papiſts and Sectaries joyntly ſay,
That other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters may as well juſtifie their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from us,
on pretence of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies retained by our Church, as we can juſtifie our
ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by reaſon of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies
injoyned by her. To which I ſhall not need to make any other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, than
a ſhort appeal to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of all unprejudiced perſons, Whether
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring the uſe of three Ceremonies
declared by her ſelf to be indifferent, and acknowledged by her enemies not
to be unlawful, can be thought by any ſober perſon to give as great, and
juſt a cauſe of Separation: from her, as all <pb facs="tcp:93904:14"/>that load of
Superſtition in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> of which St.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in his days, that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> yoke
was leſs heavy. To require Prayers in an unknown Tongue, and to Saints and
Angels is doubtleſs more offenſive, than to uſe a ſolemn plain form of
words, taken either from the Scripture, or the ancient Liturgies of the Church.
What is the Surplice, Croſs in Baptiſm, and kneeling at the Sacrament for
devotion, if compared to their Adoration of the tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated Hoſt,
worſhipping of Images, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Saints, their doctrines of the Popes
Supremacy, and Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, of Purgatory and Indulgences, beſides the
innumerable ceremonies daily practiſed by them? And as the Sectaries will not
condemn the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for receding from theſe extreams,
ſo neither can the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> blame her for want of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
in retaining both purity of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and decency of Worſhip, and abhorring
thoſe other extreams of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge and profanation of holy things, of
Rebellion and Bloud-ſhed, though under pretence of Religion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with 
<pb facs="tcp:93904:14"/>both they and the Sectaries have defiled themſelves. It was the
pious care of the Pilots of our Church, to conduct their Succeſſors
(between the two rocks of Superſtition and Idolatry on one hand, and
irreverence and irreligion on the other) in the ſame courſe in which (I
hope we all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) they themſelves went to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And the Governors of
the Church have ever ſince taken caution of all its Miniſters, not to
depart from the ſame, either in their publick mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations or doctrines,
ſo that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple need not doubt of their ſecurity in ſuch good old
ways, wherein, as the ancient <hi>Martyrs</hi> did, they may even in the
midſt of outward troubles, find peace in their Souls. But as for thoſe that
give themſelves up to the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Unſtable men, (who have degenerated
not only from the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and charity of the ancient Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,
but even from their own principles, and neither are what they lately were, nor
have given their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers any ſecurity, that they will continue to be what
now they are) They muſt needs be like children, toſſed to and 
<pb facs="tcp:93904:15"/>fro with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſlight of men, and
cunning crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whereby they lye in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. There are perhaps
ſome weak perſons among us, whoſe Conſciences are really offended at
the uſe of our Ceremonies, theſe we ought to regard ſo far, that if it
were in our power, we ſhould rather omit the uſe of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, than
give them offence. But as we are forbid to give any offence to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
perſons, ſo much more to the Church of God, 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.</note> by our
diſobedience. And whereas thoſe that have real ſcruples of Conſcience
will be diligent to enquire, and ready to receive ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, from their
more learned Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, it cannot be preſumed that there are many ſuch
among us, who have the arguments and examples of the firſt Reformers and
<hi>Martyrs,</hi> the fence and Harmony of the Reformed Churches abroad, the
deliberate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church and State at home, to inſtruct them
in the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Obedience in ſuch indifferent things; and if weak
perſons will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend rather to the wicked ſuggeſtions of a few
diſcontented and turbulent <pb facs="tcp:93904:15"/>men, <hi>Qui obſtruunt pectora
hominum, ut ante nos odiſſe incipiant, quam noſſe,</hi> that ſo Lord
it over the Conſciences of weak perſons, as to make them hate their
Brethren, they know not for what; if they neglect to hear the Church, and
deſpiſe inſtruction, and chooſe their own deluſions, they are no
longer weak Brethren, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Calv. <hi>Inſtitut. l.</hi> 3.
<hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>S.</hi> 11.</note> but reſolved adverſaries, and of
ſuch Chriſt ſays, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14. <hi>Let them alone, they be
blind Leaders of the blind.</hi> And that moſt diſſenters among us are of
this kind, may appear from that ready conformity, which they practiſed
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the late Indulgence, and ſince that upon the teſt, which argues,
their revolt to proceed from humor, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt rather than from
Conſcience. And as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> 13.</note> If ſuch weak perſons
never grow ſo ſtrong as to digeſt inoffenſive and ſlender food, it is
certain they were never well nurſed with Milk. I conclude therefore with
<hi>Peter Martyr:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Loc. Com.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi>
32.</note> We muſt not always yield to the weak in things indifferent, but
ſo long only, until they have been well inſtructed, after which, if they
are ſtill ſcrupulous, their infirmity <pb facs="tcp:93904:16"/>deſerves no farther
reſpect, for then 'tis not <hi>Scandalum puſillorum ſed
Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaeorum.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Calv. <hi>ubi ſupra S.</hi> 12.</note> And the
Church hath a neceſſity of vindicating her liberty when by the unjuſt
actions of falſe Apoſtles it is queſtioned and indanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the
Conſciences of her weak Children.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93904:16"/>
            <head>MISERICORDIAM VOLO: <hi>OR, THE PHARISEES</hi> LESSON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. ix. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>But go ye, and learn what that meaneth, I will have Mercy, and
not Sacrifice.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O find the genuine ſenſe of theſe words, it will be
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to conſult the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, from <hi>v.</hi> 9. where our Saviour
calls <hi>Matthew,</hi> a Publican of no ſmall reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and wealth, to
follow him who had not a houſe where to reſt his head. A ſtrange ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
(by virtue of two words) wrought on <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93904:17"/>ſuch a Subject; of
which we are obliged to ſay ſomething, <hi>Ne arreptitiam &amp;
enthyſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam converſionem expectemus,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Janſenius in
Locum</hi>) leſt we alſo ſhould expect (what too many pretend unto) an
inſtantaneous and impulſive power to work irreſiſtibly upon us for our
Converſion. <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Porphyry</hi> do both object this very
inſtance, to overthrow the credit of the Goſpel, as if the whole Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
of it were fictitious and falſe, or at leaſt to prove that they were no
other than giddy and fanatick perſons, that followed our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: 
<note place="margin">In locum.</note> Of this S. <hi>Hierome</hi>
takes notice, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers thus, <hi>Fulgor ipſe &amp; Majeſtas
Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis occultae, quae etiam in humanâ facie reluce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, ex primo ad
ſe videntes-trahere poterat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu. Si enim in magnete, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this reply is not thought ſufficient by learned Men, to
ſilence the objection, to which it is anſwered more ſatisfactorily, as
followeth. That <hi>S. Matthew</hi> was brought up in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi>
Religion, wherein that he was a good proficient, appears, as from many
paſſages in that Goſpel, ſo eſpecially by the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue,
wherein he wrote it. In his time the coming of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was
generally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by that Nation, and our Saviour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving entred on his
publick Office, proclaims himſelf to be that <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and proves
it, not only by the Divine Doctrine which he taught, but by the Miracles
wrought by him, ſuch as no other Man did. One was newly effected on the
Paralytick Man, <hi>v.</hi> 2d. whoſe bodily Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93904:17"/>being cured by two words, <hi>Ariſe,</hi> and <hi>walk,</hi> was
applyed by our Saviour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the People, that he could as eaſily and
graciouſly pardon their ſins. Now St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> living in
<hi>Capernaum</hi> where this was done, could not be ignorant of the fact, nor
can we probably ſuppoſe him negligent, to certifie himſelf of the real
truth of that and other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, which our Saviour wrought in
<hi>Caper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naum;</hi> and comparing the predictions of the Prophets, (with which
he was well acquainted) with the ſeveral circumſtances of the time and
place, and the mighty deeds of the promiſed <hi>Meſſias,</hi> he was
perſwaded to believe him to be the <hi>Christ;</hi> of which (it is alſo
probable that) our Saviour more fully convinced him by ſome particular
arguments, beſides the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Doctrine which he taught in that City,
although only the cloſe of that Diſcourſe be recorded; ſo that he was
not converted as St. <hi>Paul</hi> was, by a Miracle from Heaven, but by the
ordinary rational method, by which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to draw other ſinners
to himſelf, 
<note place="margin">Acts 26.18</note> 
               <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening their eyes, and
turning them from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto light, and from the power of Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
God.</hi> It is no 
<note n="*" place="margin"> Thus we find that <hi>Xenophon</hi>
became the Diſciple of <hi>Socrates;</hi> for meeting him in a narrow
paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Xenophon</hi> asked him this ſhort queſtion,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>(i.)</hi> How the neceſſaries of life might be
obtained? to which having anſwered ſatisfactorily, he demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>(i.)</hi> Where Men might be made good and virtuous?
<hi>Socrates</hi> anſwered, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>(i.)</hi> Come and
learn, whereupon <hi>Xenophon</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and became his Diſciple.
<hi>Diog. Laertius in vitá Xeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phont.</hi>
               </note> wonder then, that
Saint <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93904:18"/>
               <hi>Matthew</hi> follows ſuch an effectual call, and
without farther conſultation with fleſh and bloud, leaves all and follows
his Saviour. We ſay not then that our Converſion is the work of an
inſtant, nor that it comes with ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that we can ordinarily
point at the time and place, and ſay, <hi>Lo here,</hi> or <hi>loe there</hi>
it was; the work is done gradually, and not in a moment, rationally and not
violently, in a ſoft calm voice, and not in a Whirlwind, that carries us
irreſiſtibly, and in a manner unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable, to an eſtate of grace.
Whatever impulſes ſome Men may have on their ſpirits, to believe
themſelves thus ſanctified, they will find at laſt that God was not in
that Wind, for although it be violent, it is not long, and though it might
ſhake the heart, yet it doth not ſweep it, it is a work of time and
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian circumſpection, to <hi>make our calling and election
ſure.</hi> St. <hi>Matthew</hi> having found the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and
become his Diſciple, partly in gratitude to his Saviour, and partly in
charity to his neighbours, that they might partake of the ſame grace with
himſelf, invites them to his Houſe, where, as St. <hi>Mark</hi> ſays, Ch.
2.15. <hi>As Jeſus ſate at meat, many publicans and ſinners ſate alſo
with Jeſus, and his Diſciples.</hi> The <hi>Phariſees</hi> obſerving
our Saviour too fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar (as they thought) with Publicans and ſinners,
inſinuate this objection to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Why eateth your Maſter
with Publicans and Sinners?</hi> v. 11. To this our Saviour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth by a
three-fold Argument; The firſt of <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93904:18"/>Reaſon, in a
proverbial ſpeech, <hi>The whole need not the Phyſician, but they that are
ſick:</hi> The 2d. from Scripture, <hi>I will have mercy, and not
ſacrifice:</hi> The 3d. from the end of his coming, which was, <hi>not to
call the Righteous, but Sinners to repentance.</hi> The Text is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
of theſe Arguments, and I cannot omit a ſhort remark upon our Saviour's
Preface; for, whereas he converſed in a familiar manner with the Publicans
and Sinners, he turns off the Phariſees, who pretended to more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and
piety than others, with an imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ignorance, and Uncharitableneſs,
<hi>faceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,</hi> Get you home, and ſtudy your own duty to God, and
your neighbours, and trouble not your ſelves or others about ſuch niceties
of the Law. Go learn what that meaneth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By Mercy we are to
underſtand, <hi>Quicquid humanitatis fratri debemus,</hi> all thoſe offices
of Humanity, or Chriſtianity, which we owe to our ſelves or Brethren,
whether in reſpect of their Souls, or Bodies, goods, or good names; and by
Sacrifice (which being the chief part of God's publick Worſhip among the
<hi>Jews,</hi> is put for the whole) <hi>Totum externum cultum,</hi> all the
Paedagogy of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſcipline, of which only the Phariſees
were zealous, to the neglect of the weightier matters of the Law, Judgment,
Mercy, and Faith: And now I ſhall need onely to intreat you to read over the
whole Verſe in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.6. from whence the Text is taken, for a
full expoſition of it, where it is thus written, <hi>I deſired mercy, and
not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93904:19"/>and the knowledge of God, more than
burnt-offerings;</hi> the latter part whereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exegetical of the former
gives us this ſenſe, <hi>I deſired mercy, more than ſacrifice,</hi> for
the <hi>Hebrews</hi> wanting the termes of compariſon, do uſe the negative,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth <hi>prae,</hi> as in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi>
8.10. <hi>I deſired inſtruction,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and not
ſilver; and knowledge</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>rather than fine
gold:</hi> where the negative is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive, but comparative, for when
two things come into compariſon, it is uſual with the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> to
deny of that which is leſs, and to affirm of that which is more excellent.
And this may help us to underſtand many places of Scripture, which without
this knowledge of the <hi>Hebrew Idiom,</hi> ſeem very difficult, as
<hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> 7.22. <hi>I ſpake not to your Fathers concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
burnt-offerings and ſacrifices but this thing commanded I them,</hi>
ſaying, <hi>Obey my voice, and I will be your God, and ye ſhall be my
People,</hi> which cannot be underſtood, as if God had not commanded them
concerning Sacrifices, but that he did not require them chiefly, or
principally; Obedience being the duty which was moſt aimed at: So in the New
Teſtament. <hi>John</hi> 7.16. <hi>My Doctrine is not mine, but his that
ſent me:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.17.</note> So St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays,
<hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel;</hi> and
<hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. <hi>It is not in him that willeth, nor in him that runneth,
but in God that ſheweth mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> where our endeavours are not excluded,
but the grace of God preferred. Sacrifice <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93904:19"/>then, as it
imports the publick worſhip of God, is not excluded. God that made our Souls
and Bodies, 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</note> requires that we
ſhould glorifie him in our Souls and in our Bodies which are his, and that we
may ſerve him acceptably, he requireth outward reverence, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.</note> as well as inward
fear; and therefore to forſake the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of our ſelves, or in our
Aſſemblies not to uſe that ſolemn Unity and reverence which may
manifeſt our awful apprehenſions of that great Majeſty, with whom we have
to do, and which may add a beauty to holineſs, is a gloſs beſides this
Text, as if God had ſaid, <hi>Sacrificium nolo,</hi> I eare not whether ye
worſhip me publickly or no, whether it be at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or on
mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> whether ye keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my
San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, whether ye agree in thoſe things which ye ſhall ask, or pray
<hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> or whether ye pray ſitting or ſtanding by
your ſelves apart, as the <hi>Phariſee</hi> did, as if God were indeed the
Author of confuſion, and not of Peace and Order.</p>
            <p>Secondly, 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</note> When God ſays
<hi>Miſerioordiam volo,</hi> He doth not exclude Juſtice, for though his
tender Mercy be over all his works, yet the Judge of all the earth will do
right. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Judgment were the two great ſtrings that ſounded ſo
harmoniouſly in <hi>Davids</hi> Harp, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.1. God requireth
of us, firſt to do juſtice, and then to love mercy, <hi>Micah</hi> 6.8. If
private perſons may defend their juſt rights, without violation of the
rules of Charity, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93904:20"/>much more may ſuch as are publick
perſons, who may not ſhew mercy, but with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to the publick
peace and truth. By the Laws of God and man we are to give the precedence to
acts of Juſtice, before the works of Mercy. He doth not hate his fleſh,
that ſuffers a gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green'd member to be cut off, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>I wiſh they were
even cut off that trouble you,</hi> ſays the meekeſt Apoſtle. When
particular offenders grow obſtinate, and incorrigible, it is an act of Mercy
to make them a Sacrifice to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick juſtice. If the offence be not
capital, his puniſhment may be a means to reclaim him; if it be, the example
of his ſufferings may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter others from the like ſins, when <hi>they
ſhall hear, 
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deutr.</hi> 13.11.</note> and fear and do no
more ſo wickedly:</hi> and ſo it may prove a means of preventing the
judgments of God from falling down upon the Land. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 59.5.</note> God himſelf will
not be merciful to them that offend of malicious wickedneſs, though he have
ſaid <hi>Miſericordiam volo,</hi> I will have mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which
words commend unto us this ſeaſonable and neceſſary inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
that</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
               </label> To be buſie and ſcrupulous about the
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal worſhip of God, to the neglect of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral duties to God and our
Brethren, is a <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical</hi> temper, contrary to the Will of God.</p>
            <p>For the proof of which poſition, I ſhall weigh Mercy and
Sacrifice in the ballance of the Sanctuary, that you may clearly ſee of what
different eſteems they are in the ſight of <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93904:20"/>God. And
firſt, of Sacrifice, whoſe Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity might juſtly gain a great
veneration among that people; for though I do not think it as ancient, as the
ſtate of Innocency, (as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> and <hi>Greg. de Valentia</hi>
(the better to countenance their Sacrifice of the Maſs) do affirm,
<hi>Bellar. de miſſâ l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Valent. de
miſſae Sacrif. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.) yet it is almoſt as old as
<hi>Adam,</hi> who taught his Sons to offer both of the fruits of the earth,
and the fatlings of the Flock, which was done, as ſome learned men affirm,
immediately upon that Covenant made to the promiſed ſeed, which was
ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized by Sacrifices, as the Apoſtle intimates, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.18.
&amp; 22. And the Skins wherewith we find <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi>
clothed, ſhortly after the fall, and which were afterward made the Prieſts
portion, <hi>Levit.</hi> 8.8. were given them by God, (he having firſt had
the fleſh in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice) to be <hi>Symbolum propitiationis</hi> a ſign of
that Propitiation by which their ſins were covered.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Sacrifices were of greater eſteem for their
Inſtitution, than their Antiquity, God himſelf having commanded the
ſeveral ſorts of them, and the particular circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces concerning them.
As firſt the Peace-offering, for the fruits of the earth. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the
Sin-offering, for Atonement and pardon of Tranſgreſſions. Thirdly, the
Burnt-offering, as an acknowledgment of Homage to God the Soveraign Lord of
all. The book of <hi>Leviticus</hi> is but a Directory for theſe.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93904:21"/>
            <p>Thirdly, They were very conſiderable for their uſefulneſs.
Firſt, as they were to be <hi>Signa innocentiae,</hi> teſtimonies and
declarations of Innocency. For as the creatures offered unto God ought to be
only ſuch as were clean for their kind, ſo particularly they ought to be
without ſpot or blemiſh; and no beaſts or birds of prey, but the Ox and
the Lamb; the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and the Dove, harmleſs and uſeful crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures only,
muſt be brought to the Altar, and the offerer was to lay his hands on the
beaſt, either to profeſs his innocence, that he was not guilty of bribes or
of bloud, of fraud or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or if he were, then to confeſs his ſins,
and deprecate the wrath of God by virtue of that Covenant, whereof the
Sacrifice was a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and ſo it was propitiatory. They were,
Secondly, Euchariſtical pledges, and earneſts of their gratitude,
expreſſing their readineſs to forgce all, or to return it to him from
whom they received it. Thirdly, they were Admonitions to the guilty perſons,
to repent of their ſins, or elſe that they muſt periſh as thoſe
beaſts did.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, By external Sacrifices they were minded of their
internal duties, as <hi>mactare propriam voluntatem,</hi> to mortifie all
beaſtly luſts and affections.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, They were fences and boundaries to the Religion, God
commanding the <hi>Jews</hi> to Sacrifice thoſe very beaſts which their
Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous neighbours did worſhip (as the Ox, the Sheep, and Dove, which
were worſhipped <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93904:21"/>as Gods, among the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and
<hi>Zabii</hi>) to maintain a greater deteſtation of Idolatry in their
hearts.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, They were as ſo many penalties, and forfeitures, taken
on that people upon every treſpaſs, which alſo ſerved, not only as a
preſent puniſhment, but a future terror, minding them that they had
forfeited their own lives and Souls, which God was pleaſed to ſpare,
expecting better obedience, even a living Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>And yet all this notwithſtanding, though Sacrifices were
venerable for their Antiquity, more for their uſefulneſs, as well to the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in general, as to the Reformation of particular perſons, but moſt
of all, for its divine Inſtitution, the <hi>Levitical</hi> Law being but a
Rubrick or directory for the Sacrifices, <hi>Miſericordiam volo, &amp;c. I
will have mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if hypocritical <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould have amaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all
theſe Sacrifices in one, as the Prophet <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.21. ſpeaks, <hi>Put
your burnt-offerings to your Sacrifices and eat fleſh;</hi> If they ſhould
go with their Flocks, and heards to ſeek the Lord, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.6. If
they ſhould have preſented a Sacrifice as magnificent as that of
<hi>Solomon,</hi> 22000 Oxen, and 120000 Sheep; 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.63.</note> If they ſhould
have invented more coſtly ones, thouſands of Rams, and ten thouſand
rivers of Oil, their firſt-born for their tranſgreſſion, the fruit of
their bodies, for the ſin of their Souls; yet to do juſtice, and to love
mercy, is preferred to them all, <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93904:22"/>
            <p>For though Sacrifices were commanded, yet not for any
intrinſical goodneſs in them, but with reſpect to ſome greater good.
<hi>Eze.</hi> 20.25. <hi>I gave them Statutes that were not good, and judgments
whereby they ſhould not live,</hi> they were not originally good, as the
duties of the Moral Law, theſe were commanded becauſe they were good, the
other good only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were commanded, they did not make the Offerer,
but he made them accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as in the caſe of <hi>Cain</hi> and
<hi>Abel.</hi> Thus God ſpeaks to wicked men, 
<note place="margin">ver. 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. that
gave their mouths to evil, and did ſit and ſpeak againſt their Brother
and ſlander their own mothers ſon, <hi>I will not reprove thee for thy
Sacrifices, or burnt-offerings, Offer to God Thanksgiving, &amp;c.</hi> And
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.16. <hi>Thou deſireſt not Sacrifice, elſe would I
give it thee. The Sacrifices of God, are a broken Spirit, a broken and a
contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe. Solomon</hi> tells us [after
that he had preſented that coſtly Sacrifice] <hi>To do juſtice and
judgment, is more acceptable to the Lord than Sacrifice, Prov.</hi> 21.3. for
it is true of the houſe of God, what he ſays of ours, <hi>Better is a dry
morſel with quietneſs, than a houſe full of Sacrifices with ſtrife,
Prov.</hi> 17.1. In this therefore, the young Scribe was better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
than theſe Phariſees, for he conſented with our Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi>
12.33. <hi>That to love the Lord, with all our heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and our
neighbours as our ſelves, is more than all whole burnt-offerings, and
Sacrifice.</hi> In a word, our <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93904:22"/>Saviour hath told us, that
whatever our gift be that we bring to the Altar, if we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that our
Brother hath ought againſt us, <hi>(i.)</hi> if we are conſcious of any
injury, or unkindneſs, wherewith he may charge us, it is our duty to go
firſt, and be reconciled to our Brother, before we preſume to offer our
gift, though it be of prayer, or praiſe; God will never accept of a
peace-offering, from them that live in enmity with their Brethren.</p>
            <p>And now if I ſhould put into this ſcale, the whole Oeconomy of
the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> diſcipline, their Oblations and Incenſe, their New
Moons and Sabbaths, their calling of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies (for Feaſts or Faſts,)
and their Prayers too, as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.11. they would for want of mercy
be found too light. <hi>To what purpoſe are they?</hi> ſaith God,
<hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Who hath required this at your hands?</hi> v. 12. <hi>Bring
no more vain Oblations, incenſe is an abomination to me. I cannot away with
it, it is iniquity even your ſolemn-meetings,</hi> ver. 13. they were
eſteemed but mock ſervices by God, for want of mercy to their Brethren.</p>
            <p>Two other inſtances I ſhall add, becauſe they ſeem of
great weight.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That of Circumciſion, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods Covenant
with <hi>Abraham</hi> by which he promiſed to be his God and the God of his
ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. and the Apoſtle-calls it a Seal of the
Righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. And as God inſtituted it,
ſo he commanded the obſervation of it by a ſevere Sanction. <hi>The
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed was to be cut off, Gen.</hi> 17.14. <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93904:23"/>And
the Rabbies tell us, that as God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted deſtroying Angels to that end,
ſo he aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed guardian-Angels to every one that was Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.
Certain it is, that they bearing the marks and tokens of Gods Covenant in their
fleſh, did boaſt themſelves to be Gods pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar people. And as our
Apoſtle intimates, they preferred it to the Croſs of Chriſt which the
Apoſtle, though he himſelf was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, abhors with an <hi>abſit,
Gal.</hi> 6. ver. 14. But it was a ſaying among the <hi>Jews,</hi> that
Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was equal to the keeping of the whole Law, and that Heaven
&amp; Earth could not ſtand if Circumciſion were omitted, therefore they
made the eight days before Circumciſion to be a preparation for that
ſolemnity at which they invited their friends as witneſſes and Sponſors
for the child, that he ſhould obſerve the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the God of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> and in the later times, had always an empty Chair ſet for
<hi>Elias,</hi> expecting that he ſhould deſcend from Heaven to be a
witneſs of the Circumciſion; and yet in truth it was as the Apoſtle
ſaith, a a burthen which neither they nor their Fathers could bear, and
therefore God himſelf diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the uſe of it to this people
forty years together in the wilderneſs; 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.</note> and though St.
<hi>Paul</hi> was Circumciſed, and to make his own and <hi>Timothy</hi>'s
miniſtry the more acceptable to that people, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.1.</note> took <hi>Timothy</hi>
and Circumciſed him, yet he teacheth them that if they were Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<hi>(i. e.)</hi> with an intention to obtain Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by the works of the
Law, Chriſt ſhould <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93904:23"/>profit them nothing: And
<hi>Galatians</hi> 6.15. (to them that were) <hi>in Christ Jeſus, neither
circumciſion availed any thing, neither uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but a new
creature;</hi> by which he underſtands, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. <hi>faith which
worketh by love:</hi> And in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19. <hi>a keeping the
Commandments of God:</hi> ſo that circumciſion was not to be contended for,
when the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Goſpel, or Charity came into competition with
it.</p>
            <p>A ſecond inſtance ſhall be that of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi>
Sabbath, of the profanation whereof the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> complained to
Chriſt of his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.2. and for whoſe vindication
our Saviour urgeth again the right underſtanding of this Text, <hi>v.</hi> 7.
<hi>If ye had known what this meaneth, I will have mercy and not ſacrifice,
ye would not have condemned the guiltleſs.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Chriſt's
Diſciples (as well as himſelf) were circumciſed, and ſo obliged to
ſanctifie the Sabbath according to the Commandment, and great were the
puniſhments which God threatned and inflicted on the tranſgreſſors,
ſuch as ſtruck a terror to them, which made them run into ſuperſtition,
inſomuch that they would not go out of their places, nor dreſs their meat,
nor carry a ſtick, nor defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt their enemies on that
day. And the crime for which the Diſciples were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, was rather
for tranſgreſſing their tradition, than any precept of God; for if the
fault was their walking through the Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields, it doth not appear that they
exceeded <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93904:24"/>2000. Cubits, which was allowed by them for a
Sabbath-days Journey; if plucking the ears of Corn, that was approved by the
Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.25. If for eating (which ſeemeth moſt probable,
becauſe our Saviour anſwered the objection by the inſtance of
<hi>David</hi>'s eating the ſhew-bread) yet being hungry, their
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity might excuſe them, nor was this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden (though perhaps
contrary to a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious practice of theirs, for which the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
upbraided them, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> their Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days Faſts) therefore Chriſt
vindicates them, as guiltleſs upon the Plea in the Text, <hi>I will have
mercy, &amp;c.</hi> As if he had ſaid, You Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees do not underſtand
the ſubſtantial and ſpiritual part of your own Law, for as long as there
is not contumacy or contempt in the neglect of Ceremonial Precepts, but the
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of a juſt neceſſity, or the rational conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of a
greater good to out-weigh that neglect, God will not impute it as a ſin. Of
this our Saviour convinceth them by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>David, v.</hi> 4.
and of the Prieſts in the Temple, profaning the Sabbath by dreſſing the
Sacrifices, for they were wont to ſay— <hi>In the Temple there is no
Sabbath.</hi> If then the ſervice of the Temple excuſed the Prieſts for
profaning the Sabbath; the ſervice of Chriſt who tells them of himſelf,
that he was greater than the Temple, <hi>v.</hi> 6. might excuſe his
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, who being Prophets and Preachers of the Kingdom of Heaven, were
greater than the Prieſts of the Law, as our Saviour ſaid of <hi>John</hi>
the Baptiſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.11.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93904:24"/>
            <p>Now a Prophet even under the Law, was above the Law of the Temple,
and might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice in any place, as <hi>Elias</hi> did, and therefore it
could not be unlawful for Chriſt's Diſciples, ſo earneſtly attending
his work, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came hungry, having no other proviſion, to eat a few
grains of Corn for their preſent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. Again, our Saviour tells them,
<hi>v.</hi> 8. that the Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath, which that he
ſpeaks of himſelf as the <hi>Meſſias</hi> (who had power to abrogate
and alter the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath) is the opinion of ſome, though not ſo clear,
becauſe <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.20. he would not have it yet known that he was the
<hi>Meſſias,</hi> and if our Saviour had made this his argument he needed
not to have uſed any other. Others therefore think that by the Son of Man is
meant <hi>every Son of Man,</hi> for Chriſt himſelf was not blamed but his
Diſciples, whom he pronounceth guiltleſs for this reaſon, <hi>The Son of
Man is Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> which S. <hi>Mark</hi> expreſſeth more
plainly to this purpoſe, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27. <hi>The Sabbath was made for
man:</hi> and ſo the argument ſtands thus, That which was made for another
thing is to give place to that for which it was made, but <hi>the Sabbath was
made for man, ergo, &amp;c.</hi> Now though the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo
ſuperſtitious, that even in the time of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> they would
not defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt their enemies on the Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, yet
ſhortly after they began to grow wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and would not only deſend their
own Lives, but aſſault their enemies, and do any <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93904:25"/>neceſſary work; for they had dearly been taught this Maxime,
<hi>Periculum vitae diſſolvit Sabbatum,</hi> that the danger of loſing
Life did diſſolve the Sabbath: And as <hi>Selden, de Jure Gentium, l.</hi>
2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. they held that in caſe of ſickneſs, a <hi>Jew</hi>
might not only eat forbidden Meats, but for recovery of health, or avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
of any great danger, he might break any commandment, except theſe three,
<hi>(viz.)</hi> I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Murther, and Inceſt; and I have heard from the
mouth of a modern <hi>Jew,</hi> an odd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of that Text,
<hi>Pro.</hi> 4.4. which he interpreting the copulative, by a diſcretive;
reads, <hi>Keep the commandments, but live;</hi> i. e. ſo keep the
commandments, as to be careful of preſerving thy life in keeping of them. But
to return in our Saviour's time, it was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by them, as a thing lawful
on the Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, 
<note place="margin">Luk. 13.15</note> to pluck an Oxe or an Aſs
out of a Ditch, or to lead them to Water, and to permit Merchants and Carriers
to travel about their neceſſary affairs on that Day. So that the ſum of
all is this, that when two Laws ſeemed to interfere, ſo as both could not
be kept, the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer muſt yield to the greater, the ritual and
ceremonial, to the moral or evangelical, which is the ſenſe of the Text:
<hi>I will have mercy, and not ſacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be objected, What is this of the contention of the
<hi>Jews</hi> for Ceremonies, to the contending of Chriſtians againſt them,
when they are impoſed contrary to their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty?</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93904:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe Objectors do no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their
Chriſtian liberty, than the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees did the right meaning of the Text,
which equally concludes againſt them that contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ceremonies, as
them that contend for them, to the breach of Charity, Obedience, and Publick
Peace, which as I have already proved againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> out of their
Law, ſo I ſhall prove it <hi>(contra Gentes)</hi> againſt conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
Chriſtians out of the Goſpel. — Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty is the
reſtoring of Mankind by Chriſt to ſuch an eſtate as it was in, before
the Ceremonial Law was impoſed, ſo that now <hi>every Creature of God is
good,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. <hi>nothing is of it ſelf unclean, Titus</hi>
1.15. <hi>but all things are lawful,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. (i. e.) it is
lawful for a Chriſtian to do thoſe things, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which nothing of
moment can be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Scriptures, or right reaſon, to prove them
unlawful. Thoſe Men therefore go the wrong way, and puzle their own and other
Mens conſciences, who argue, It is not commanded, therefore I may not do it;
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they ought to argue, It is not forbidden, therefore I may do it
without prejudice to my Chriſtian liberty: although it may be truly ſaid,
that it is commanded of God <hi>(in genere)</hi> from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.
and <hi>(in specie)</hi> by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to which we are bound to yield
obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for conſcience ſake, not as if the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of our Superiors
did immediately bind the conſcience in ſuch caſes, but by vertue of God's
commands for obedience to the higher <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93904:26"/>powers. The truth of
all this will appear, from the Apoſtles own practice, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28.
who impoſed on the Primitive Chriſtians ſuch things, as were in their
nature indifferent, to be obſerved as neceſſary, <hi>bono pacis,</hi>
ſo <hi>Piſcator, Non ſemper &amp; ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, nec per ſe &amp;
ſimpliciter ad ſalutem neceſſaria, ſed ad pacem Eccleſiae &amp;
vitandas offenſiones, ut aleretur mutua benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia inter Judaeos &amp;
Gentiles:</hi> The ſenſe whereof I ſhall give you from the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations on the place, The word neceſſary is not
referred to the Ceremonies, but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion, and perſons
whoſe Salvation and Unity was neceſſary. Now who dares ſay, they were
not bound to obſerve thoſe Canons, when the Apoſtles ſay, it ſeemed
good to the Holy Ghoſt, as well as to them, to lay theſe things upon them,
as neceſſary to be obſerved for the time and ends above mentioned?</p>
            <p>Again, we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> commending the
<hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 1 Epiſtle, Ch. 11. v. 2. for keeping the Ordinances
which he delivered them, that is, ſay our Annotators, particular Ordinances
for comelineſs and good order, which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Eccleſiaſtical Polity,
and were afterward called Canons, againſt which, if any but only ſeemed to
be contentious by diſputing againſt them, the Apoſtle ſilenced them by
that, in Verſ. 16. <hi>We have no ſuch cuſtome, neither the Churches of
God,</hi> that is, ſay the ſame Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators, to contend about matters of
this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but willingly and cheerfully to obey thoſe that have the
over-ſight of us in the Lord And <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93904:26"/>it is fit to conſider
the nature of the matter treated of, which was, how Men and Women ought to
behave themſelves at publick Prayers, which behaviour the Apoſtle would
have to agree with thoſe ſigns and geſtures of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, 
<note place="margin">Camcron. in loc.</note> which Subjects are wont
to yield to their Princes: and although the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with
their Heads covered, which was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a ſign of reverence among them, as
alſo do the <hi>Turks</hi> to this day ſit covered, and bowing their Bodies
at their Devotions, as they are wont to do in the preſence of their Rulers;
yet the Apoſtle being to plant the Church among the <hi>Romans,</hi> and
<hi>Grecians,</hi> with whom the uncovering of the Head was a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of
reverence, he appoints the ſame beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the Worſhip of God. And this
was practiſed by the Chriſtians in <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s days, 
<note place="margin">Apologet.</note> who prayed <hi>Capite nudo,
expanſis manibus,</hi> with bare Heads, and Hands lifted up, and this
<hi>Tertullian</hi> calls <hi>legem Dei,</hi> God's Law, <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris legem
Dei? habes communem iſtam in publico mundi &amp; in naturalibus tabulis ad
quas &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolus provocare ſolet cùm in velamine faciei,
inquit, Non natura vos docet?</hi> For by Nature here, as <hi>Grotius</hi>
obſerves, ſuch general cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes as had obtained among the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> are intended, <hi>Non eſt hoc plane Naturale, 
<note place="margin">Grotius in loc.</note> ſed quod longe
late<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> receptum, ut Jurisconſulti dant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Juris Naturalis, Juri
Gentium.</hi> Our Apoſtle then in this place doth, as with a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edged Sword,
cut off all diſputations, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, againſt decent Ceremonies in the
Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93904:27"/>of God, 1. By his Apoſtolical injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
2<hi>ly,</hi> By the cuſtome of the Churches of God: and to contend about
ſuch things, and diſturb the peace of the Church is as unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, as
irreligious a thing, which is my ſecond argument, The unreaſonableneſs of
contending for Ceremonies, to the neglect of Moral duties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For it agrees with the ſentiments of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as
<hi>Plato</hi> diſcovers them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Gods reſpect
not our Sacrifices, but our Souls:</hi> And we our ſelves acknowledge not
them for our Friends, or Servants, who only complement us, or put us off with
eye-ſervice, or a little lip-labour, <hi>Quin demus Superis —
Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Jus, faſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> animi, ſanctoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> receſſus —
Mentis; &amp; incoctum Generoſo pectus honeſto: Haec cedo ut admoveam
templis, &amp; farre li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the works of Mercy are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
the reſemblances of the Divine nature, and life: <hi>Be ye merciful,</hi>
ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.36. <hi>as your Heavenly Father is
merciful. 
<note place="margin">In Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nil di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinius, in bumanitate nil
huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> Lactantius</hi> tells us, <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Religionis eſt eum
imitari quem colis,</hi> it is the perfection of Religion, to be like him, whom
we worſhip. Now <hi>God is love, and he that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in
God, and God in him,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.16. And he that loveth not his Brother, whom
he hath ſeen, how can he, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> he cannot, love his God whom he
hath <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93904:27"/>not ſeen, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.20. God hath made our
charity, and our peace, as well as our holineſs, 
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> conditions, without which we
ſhall not ſee God: The Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 6.6.</note> to inſtruct us in the
mercifulneſs of God, commends to us the knowledge of God; did we know God
better, we would love our Brethren more; 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.8. <hi>He that
loveth not, knoweth not God, for God is love.</hi> It is ſpoken of
<hi>Joſiah,</hi> that <hi>he judged the cauſe of the poor and needy, was
not this to know me, ſaith the Lord?</hi> Jer. 22.16.</p>
            <q>Heu! primae ſcelerum cauſae mortalibus aegris Naturam
neſcire Deûm. 
<bibl>
                  <hi>Sil. Ital.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>We are moſtly prepoſſeſt with unreaſonable and
uncharitable Opinions, and paſſions, which do not only diſpoſe us to
think amiſs of our Brethren, but of God alſo, 
<note place="margin">See <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.24.</note> as if he were
ſuch as our ſelves, as the <hi>Indians</hi> being black, paint their Gods
ſo too. That Man muſt needs be very unmerciful, that can think his God to
be ſo, and ſure it is, that if God ſhould be as unmerciful towards
others, as we fancy him, or as we are, there are but few that would be ſaved,
except thoſe of the ſame fraternity with our ſelves. 
<note place="margin">Jain. 3.15.</note> But ſuch black thoughts are
fruits of the ſpirit of Darkneſs; the fruits of the beſt ſpirit, are
love, joy, peace, 
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,
gentleneſs, goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall ever ſuſpect that
Religion, that teacheth Men to love God, and hate their Brethren with all their
heart.</p>
            <p>It is no wonder if the Stoicks, that deny the <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93904:28"/>Deity, and aſcribe all to an inexorable fate, do alſo unman
Humanity, and unbowel Virtue, teaching that a wiſe Man ought to caſt away
all compaſſion, and making that a defect of the Soul, <hi>viz.</hi> bearing
one anothers burthens, which a better Philoſopher ſays, 
<note place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> is to fulfill the Law of
Chriſt. Well might <hi>Cicero</hi> reject them; <hi>(neque enim audiendi
ſunt, qui virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem duram, &amp; ferream eſſe volunt)</hi> as not fit to
be heard, who would transform Virtue, which is of a gentle, tender, tractable,
and yielding quality, into a rigid, ſtupid, implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and unſociable
conſtitution: Such wiſe Men have as little brains, as bowels, ſeeing St.
<hi>James</hi> tells us, that <hi>the wiſdom that is from above, is firſt
pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and
good fruits, without partiality and without hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi> And thus,
though I have but caſually let fall ſome drops of Mercy into the other
ſcale, you may perceive how much they do out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weigh the whole
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Diſcipline and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. The treaſures of Mercy are as
bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as the Ocean, and therefore I ſhall not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to contract
them within this ſcale. <hi>My thoughts are not your thoughts, 
<note place="margin">Iſ. 55.8.</note> neither are my ways your
ways; for as the Heavens are higher than the Earth, ſo are my ways higher
than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts,</hi> ſaith the Lord. What
great things the mercy of God will effect for ſuch as love him, may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
appear by the things he works in them, and by them, whom he cauſeth to
partake of his <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93904:28"/>own ſpirit, and ſo ſheds abroad his
love into their hearts, that they can extend it again throughout the whole
World, and be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>as their Heavenly Father is merciful,</hi> even in
that great inſtance of making (as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) <hi>the ſun of
righteouſneſs to ſhine, and the Dew of Heaven to fall upon the just and
the unjust,</hi> and by their compaſſionate deſires, and faithful
prayers, their tender mercies are over all the works of God. How gladly could I
caſt my ſelf into this Ocean, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> to <hi>Euripus,</hi>
and ſay, <hi>Quoniam ego non Comprehendam te, tu Comprehendes me;</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot comprehend thy mercies, Lord, let me be comprehended of
them!</p>
            <p>But as every duſt of Gold is Gold, ſo every act of mercy is
precious, and therefore I ſhall not need to mention the infinite perfections
of Divine mercy, nor thoſe Heroick deeds of merciful Men, whoſe love hath
been more ſtrong than Death; but confine my ſelf within thoſe ordinary
bounds of Charity, wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian may and ought to converſe with
other, ſuch as the Apoſtle names, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. To be
long-ſuffering, and kind, not to envy, or vaunt themſelves, not to be
puffed up, and ſeek their own, not to be eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, not to think or
ſpeak evil: any of theſe defects will, as the want of Salt to the
Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, make it corrupt, and become unſavory. Every malicious thought
will be as ſo much fire, to make them evaporate into ſmoke. So the
Apoſtle aſſures us, 
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Though I spake with 
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93904:29"/>the tongue of men and Angels,</hi> though I had the gift of
Prophecie, and underſtand all My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and knowledge, and had all Faith,
and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing. The bare omiſſion of the
meaneſt acts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſuch as our Saviour mentioneth, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>
25.25. is ſufficient to exclude our Souls as well as our Services from
Heaven. The Phariſees then, had little reaſon to inſiſt ſo exactly on
a <hi>Levitical</hi> Ceremony of touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and accompanying with unclean
perſons; when they admitted that pride and contempt of their brethren, that
envy againſt Chriſt, which rendred them by far the more unclean. A
principle which hath much troubled the Church of God in all ages, when
<hi>Phariſaical</hi> men, firſt cenſure and condemn their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and
then ſeparate from them, and grow in hatred againſt them, when they have no
other reaſon to think ill of their Brethren, but becauſe they think too
well of themſelves; and by their zeal for the externals of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeek
to palliate their neglect of the moſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential duties. To theſe our
Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the Leſſon in the Text (as well as to thoſe ancient
<hi>Phariſees</hi>) <hi>Go learn what that meaneth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Having endeavoured to convince your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the truth
of the propoſition in general, I ſhall apply it as effectually as I can for
the cure of our preſent diſtempers, for we alſo do trouble our ſelves,
and others, about many inconſiderable circumſtances of exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93904:29"/>Worſhip, to the neglect of thoſe moral duties of
Humility, Charity and peace, which are of the very Eſſence of Religion. And
I doubt not but if we would lay aſide our pride, prejudice, and carnal
intereſt, and as new born Babes, deſire the ſincere Milk of the Word,
that we might grow thereby, this plain Leſſon of our Saviour, touching the
<hi>Love of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> would more edifie us as well in holineſs, as in
peace and love, than all the publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations or private inſinuations of
conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons, whoſe zeal (like the little im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent heat in
Inſects, which not being ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to form ſound vitals within, runs
out into many weak and uſeleſs members and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth (an
<hi>Ephemeron</hi>) an Animal that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth but for a day) running out into
many nice circumſtances, may have ſomething of the ſhew, but very little
of the ſubſtance and life of Religion. To ſuch I do in the fear of God
propoſe this method of learning the Leſſon in the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That our Agreement in the Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Religion,
and the liberty to profeſs and practiſe all things neceſſary to
Godlineſs and Salvation, ought to be an indiſſoluble bond of peace and
unity to us all. As the lower Sphears, though they have a proper tendency of
their own, yet yield to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the higher Orb; ſo though we have
ſome fond conceits, and ſmall concerns of our own, we ſhould forſake
them to comply with the great ends of Religion, Mercy, and Peace. 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93904:30"/>We agree in the ſubſtance of the Goſpel, in the
Creed, and Commandments, in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and the Sacraments; we are built
on the Foundation of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf
being the chief Corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20.</note> and on this
Foundation we may build as high as Heaven, why ſhould our Pride and
Contention pull down the Judgment of <hi>Babel</hi> upon us? Methinks there
ſhould be no place left for diſcord among Brethren that are united by ſo
many Obligations, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5.</note> one Lord, one Faith,
one Baptiſm, one God, one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all: but though we all pretend to meet
in the ſame Center, yet the Leaders in every Faction (as the Lines that are
protracted to the greateſt length) are fartheſt from recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</p>
            <p>Though others murmur and will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with <hi>Manna</hi>
except they may have their fleſh-pots too, Let us bleſs God, that he hath
eſtabliſhed truth and righteouſneſs among us by a Law. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 127.20</note> He hath not dealt
ſo with other Nations, nor was it ſo with us of late days, and we may
juſtly fear that our ingratitude and contentions may reduce us to the like
confuſion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If God himſelf will diſpenſe with all the
externals of his Worſhip, to ſhew us mercy, we need not fear his
diſpleaſure, if we either omit ſome things that pleaſe us, or admit
ſome other things that diſpleaſe us in the outward adminiſtrations, for
the freer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of mercy and peace: better it is to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to a
doubtful inconvenience, than to run <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93904:30"/>into a certain
miſchief. And it will never be accounted among our infirmities, that we were
not more careful of the publick Worſhip of God, than he himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Neither the external circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Worſhip which
are injoyned, nor thoſe which are contended for, in oppoſition to them,
have any poſitive command from God, or our Saviour; for our Saviour hath not
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the circumſtances of Divine Worſhip, foreſeeing (as Mr. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10.
<hi>n.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays) that the ſame Rites would not
agree with the ſeveral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Ages, wherein the Church ſhould be
planted; and if we conſider that whereas the Two Sacraments only are
poſitively inſtituted in the New Teſtament, there have been ſo great
controverſies moved about them, that many large Volumes have been written,
and many bloudy Battles fought by men of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary minds, it will appear a
great mercy, that other things did not come under precept; for then, greater
pretences for maintaining differences would have been pleaded, which now have
no colour, for as much as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in diſpute fall not under any command,
and if there be no command, it follows that they are left at liberty, but by
offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt plain Commands, for obedience and peace, our ſin and
condemnation are the greater.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This ſhall be a Fourth conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that whatever
cannot be referred to Faith or good manners, and is neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93904:31"/>nor forbidden, that may be done or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as is moſt
conducible to the great ends of peace, Charity, and Unity. To evince the
indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of an action, theſe things are ſufficient, Firſt, that
there be no command injoyning or forbidding it. 2<hi>ly.</hi> That it be
declared by the Magiſtrate impoſing it, that it is not intended as a part
of Divine Worſhip, as having an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent neceſſity, (and ſo becomes
an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable duty,) but for Order, Decency and Unity, and therefore as
the Caſuiſts ſay, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra contemptum &amp; ſcandalum,</hi> if the
Superiors authority be not deſpiſed, nor our Brethren ſcandalized, the
practice of ſuch things may be omitted, as you know the Ceremonies may be, in
caſe of neceſſity, and in private duties, which could not be if they were
not things indifferent. So that, that part of the Churches declaration, that
ſays, ſhe hath power to add, alter, or abrogate ſuch Rites, manifeſtly
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares their indifferency, as <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, ſpeaking of
the Sacramental Bread, whether it be Levened or unlevened, and the Wine,
whether Red or White, whether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered into every mans hand by the Deacon, or
not. <hi>Haec indifferentia ſunt &amp; in Eccleſiae libertate
poſita.</hi> The Inſtitutions and practice of the Church are a ſufficient
rule for ſuch practices. The not preſcribing them in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, argueth
that it was as unneceſſary as impoſſible to be done: for as to that
rule of the Apoſtle, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 14.23</note> that <hi>whatſoever
is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> it imports not, that we either ſhould 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93904:31"/>have a command for every action in the Word of God, or that
the thing done, is in it ſelf pleaſing to God, but, if it be not forbidden,
nor really evil, but is in order to other good ends, it may or may not be done,
(without a Superſtitious fear of offending God,) by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of our
Chriſtian liberty.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In all things not determined by the Word of God, we are
bound to obey the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, by virtue of the general Commands of God, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> and otherwiſe the
Magiſtrate ſhould have no authority at all, for thoſe things which are
good in their own nature, are commanded by God, and therefore the Magiſtrate
muſt have power in things not commanded, or he hath none at all: and ſo in
things forbidden, which will more plainly appear by what followeth,</p>
            <p>For, Sixthly, If I may do, or not do things in their nature
indifferent, rather than offend a weak Brother, (which is the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts
Plea to the Conformiſts) much more ought I ſo to do, or not do, rather than
offend a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, or diſturb the publick peace, becauſe
publick offences are more carefully to be avoided than private, and when the
Magiſtrates command is added (whether he be Civil or Eccleſiaſtical) that
which was but lawful before, becomes, <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi>
neceſſary, as a means to peace or edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.20. It is
certainly more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to oppoſe the command of many wiſe men (and
ſuch perhaps as are intruſted by us) or which is the ſame thing to go
againſt their <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93904:32"/>judgment, and offend their Conſciences,
than to go againſt the judgment, and offend the Conſciences of a few weak
Brethren, who neither have the advantages to inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the nature
of things, nor that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or concern, to provide for the publick peace,
as their Superiours have, but may be eaſily impoſed on, by crafty men that
lay in wait to deceive. Judge in your ſelves Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren how intolerable would
that Servant be in your Family that ſhould be always quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at his
Maſters habit, or the directions given him for his work; and though he have
good and wholſom food in plenty, yet diſlikes the Cookery, and being
reproved for his pride and curioſity, is obſtinate and inſtigates his
fellow-ſervants to deſert the Family. But herein the Apoſtles example may
direct us better how far we may, or may not do things indifferent, (and ſuch
as have ſome appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evil in them to others) rather than to give
offence to a Brother, as in the caſe of meats, which had been declared
unclean by the Law, (but that difference was by the Goſpel abrogated) and
were much more accounted pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted by having been offered unto Idols, yet the
Apoſtle ſays, 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8.</note> 
               <hi>meat commendeth
us not to God, for neither if we eat are we the better, neither if we eat not
are we the worſe,</hi> it is grace and not meat by which the heart is
eſtabliſhed; our Chriſtian liberty is an Amulet againſt any corruption
in ſuch things, for though the practice be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the judgment is free,
there is <hi>libertas ad op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum.</hi> 
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93904:32"/>So in the
caſe of Circumciſion before mentioned, which was ſo abrogated, that S.
<hi>Paul</hi> ſays, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>if ye be
circumciſed</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> with an opinion of the legal neceſſity of
it) <hi>Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing:</hi> Yet to the <hi>Jews,</hi>
that he might win them, he became as a <hi>Jew,</hi> and then uſed
Circumciſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. and to them that were without the Law, as
without Law, that he might win the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and then he would not
Circumciſe, and in all this he was Chriſts Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though he made
himſelf a ſervant to all.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle knew that his Chriſtian liberty was founded in
freedom of Judgment and not of practice, and that neither <hi>Circumciſion
nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion</hi> were any thing, 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.19.</note> but the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of
the Commandments. Now no actions of ours that are required in obedience to our
Superiours about the Publick Worſhip, are ſo obnoxious to cenſure and
ſcandal, as theſe were, but are under our Chriſtian liberty. And as we
ought to ſerve one another in love, in obedience to Gods commands; ſo ought
we in obedience of the ſame, to <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance
of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> and not uſe our liberty as a Cloke of
Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or an occaſion to the fleſh, to caſt off either our
Love to our Brethren or Obedience to Magiſtrates. For to what end hath God,
according to his promiſe, raiſed up Kings, to be Nurſing Fathers to his
Church, or what poſſibility is there, that they ſhould provide for its
peace, if they have not power in theſe External things? If therefore the
things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93904:33"/>be indifferent, it is certain that
obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Magiſtrate is no indifferent thing, but as neceſſary,
as peace and unity, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe be preſerved.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The means are alway, as ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient, ſo inferior
to the end: Now the end of the Commandment is Charity, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
ſaith, 
<note place="margin">Col. 3.14.</note> and therefore both he, and St.
<hi>Peter</hi> require charity above all things, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. When
therefore theſe externals of religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come apples of contention, they are
forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit, which cannot be injoyed without the breach of the great
Commandment: and if they had each of them a particular precept; yet when
leſſer duties come in competition with greater, they ceaſe to oblige.
Private Laws yield to publick, humane Laws to the Laws of God; and among God's
Laws, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Precepts yield to thoſe that are moral and natural; A Vow,
or an Oath concerning a thing lawful, if it hinder <hi>Majus bonum
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turale,</hi> ceaſeth to oblige. The <hi>Corban</hi> might not be pleaded
in Bar, to the relieving of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; much leſs may any Covenant oblige,
againſt the Peace of the Church, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Parent (as ſome ſtill
plead, for that which they call the National Covenant.) Thoſe things
therefore which are matters of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and external order, how
preciſely ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever injoyned, ought to give place to thoſe that are the
more ſubſtantial parts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch as mercy and obedience to
Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, charity, peace, and unity among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93904:33"/>and as we may diſuſe ſome things which have been
generally received in the Church of God, (as were the kiſs of charity, the
love-feaſts, and anointing of the Sick) ſo certainly we may uſe ſome
other things, which are injoyned by our Superiors, for the ſake of Order, and
Unity. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed the Doctrine of Faith in the
Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he tells them, 
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.16.</note> that if about rites and
ceremonies, <hi>Any man ſeem to be contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, we have no ſuch cuſtome,
neither the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God:</hi> that is, the cuſtom of the Church is a
ſufficient Plea againſt ſuch contentious perſons. Thus when the Council
of <hi>Nice</hi> had compoſed the Articles of Faith in that Creed, they all
with one conſent approved of the Ancient rites and cuſtomes:
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſays, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> it was
ever e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed an unreaſonable thing for thoſe that agreed in the
Subſtantials of Religion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſeparate from each
other, for cuſtomes, and matters of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſputation.</p>
            <p>And it is generally agreed, that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which are
<hi>ſui Juris,</hi> agreeing in the ſame Faith, may differ in Rites and
Ceremonies, which they have power to alter, or abrogate, and therefore
<hi>Calvin</hi> ſays, they are <hi>Mali filii,</hi> wicked Sons, that will
diſturb the Peace of the Church, their Mother, for ſuch external rites, and
as the Phariſees in the Text ſeek to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the Diſciples by ſuch
objections againſt their Maſter, <hi>Why eateth your Maſter with 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93904:34"/>Publicans and Sinners?</hi> And yet certain it is, that the
Authors of Sects and Diviſions among us, have no better grounds for all the
diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and confuſion, the proud contempt, and unchriſtian cenſures,
the ſlander and vexation, that have been as ſo many evil ſpirits raiſed
among us; and I deſire, that ſuch as are yet in the fault, would not only
conſider the inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of the grounds, but alſo the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
conſequences of our diviſions, how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſite to our Saviour's
rule in the Text, <hi>I will have mercy, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, that there are Diviſions among us, may be proved by the
ſame arguments, that the Apoſtle uſeth to prove, that there were
Diviſions in the Church of <hi>Corinth, 
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.4.</note> (viz.)</hi> when one ſaith,
<hi>I am of Paul,</hi> and another, <hi>I am of Apollos, &amp;c.</hi> which
Diviſions, as they cannot be warranted, but on a ſuppoſition of ſome
great corruption in our Doctrine, or Worſhip, or ſome grand profaneneſs
in our Members; ſo are they not raiſed without ſuch thoughts in the
hearts of thoſe that do ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from us, as Mr. <hi>Newcomen</hi>
obſerved in his Sermon at St. <hi>Pauls, Febr.</hi> 8. 1646. <hi>p.</hi> 40. 
<q rend="margQuotes">Who are they that brand their Brethren
with the title of Proud, Time-ſervers, Prelatical, Tyrannical,
Antichriſtian, but ſuch as ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate? Who will ſay that they are of the
ſame opinion in Fundamentals, and that their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences are, but <hi>in
minutioribus;</hi> but, Why do they in matters of leſſer moment
tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the Apoſtles rule? Why do they not <pb n="37" facs="tcp:93904:34"/>keep
their opinions private, and have their faith to themſelves before God? Why do
they upon ſo ſmall differences, withdraw from Communion with us, and gather
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into diſtinct and ſeparate Churches?</q> This is certainly a
Phariſaical leaven, that fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and imbitters our ſpirits, and though
the effects of it may be hid for a time, yet on every heat and agitation it
ſpreads through the whole lump, and ſwells Men with Pride, and an
unſociable ſowrneſs of Spirit.</p>
            <p>And though the things wherein we differ, ſeem to be but ſmall,
and have a ſhew of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet the conſequences are ſo notoriouſly and
really evil, that the moſt zealous preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the Diſcipline of
Chriſt, are too nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Plaiſter to cover or cure the feſtred rancor
and malice towards his members. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are no fit matter to exerciſe our
zeal and contention, but obedience and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Yet as the Ordinances and
Rites that were retained by the believing <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi>
were ſtill a Wall of ſeparation between them, and the Apoſtle calls it
<hi>the enmity,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.15.</note> ſo is it with us: The
<hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered chiefly about the place wherein
they ought to Worſhip, upon which there grew a mortal hatred between them,
ſo as that there was no commerce between them, they would not ſalute one
another.—<hi>Nec monſtrare vias eadem niſi Sacra colenti;</hi> and it
was accounted all one to be a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and to have a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. So when
once Men ſwerve from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="38" facs="tcp:93904:35"/>and baſis of charity,
there is no conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but Men fall, firſt to vain jangling, and that
increaſeth to more ungodlineſs, for where bitter envying, or (as the
original word is) zeal is, there is confuſion, and every evil thing.
<hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James, how great a matter a little fire
kindleth;</hi> if Men ſnatch a Coal from the Altar, it is blown up and down
by popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar breath, until it be raiſed into a flame, and hath this property
at leaſt of the fire of the Sanctuary, that the buſie Levites will not
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to go out.</p>
            <p>I know it will be troubleſome to others, for it is a terror to
my ſelf to recount, what cataracts and inundations of blood, our
Church-diviſions, that at firſt, as the prophets Cloud, were but as a
hand-breadth, have rained down upon the whole Land. I ſhall give it you
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a Foreign inſtance, namely of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts</hi> in
<hi>Africa:</hi> who, becauſe <hi>Cecilian</hi> their Biſhop had admitted
ſome to his Communion, whom they accuſed for <hi>Traditors,</hi> firſt
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew from the Church, which as they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ought to conſiſt of
ſuch only as were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, holy, and without blemiſh: and
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had read in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi>
cauſed his Flock to reſt <hi>ſub meridie,</hi> they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that
their Party in the South of <hi>Africa,</hi> was that Flock; and hereupon they
are very induſtrious to gather Congregations, and pick up one of a Family,
and two or three of a Village, which, as <hi>Optatus</hi> obſerves, were
ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of the weaker ſort. <hi>Aut exivit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor <pb n="39" facs="tcp:93904:35"/>&amp; reſedit Maritus, &amp;c.</hi> The Wife is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from her
Husband, the Son or Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er
from their Parents. And my 
<note n="*" place="margin">Optatus.</note> Author ſets down the
Method which thoſe Seducers uſed, <hi>Cai Sei!</hi> or <hi>Caia Scia! bonus
homo, ſed tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, libera animam tuam:</hi> Thou good Man, or good Woman,
thou art among Idolaters, and Superſtitious perſons, thou haſt good
affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but they are not rightly placed, come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and
deliver thy Soul: When they had thus increaſed their Party, they built
<hi>Baſilicas non neceſſarias,</hi> more Churches than were
neceſſary, and their Sermons were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Satyrs againſt the
Catholicks, and though they were frequently confuted in private
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, and condemned by many Synods at home, and ſeveral Councils
abroad, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Edicts of the Emperors, yet never would they acquieſce,
or be reconciled, but vexed the Churches of <hi>Africa</hi> for more than a
Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years, increaſing their Numbers, and ſubdividing into Factions, as
the <hi>Primianists</hi> and <hi>Maximianiſts,</hi> the <hi>Rogatians</hi>
and <hi>Callidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Luciferians</hi> and <hi>Circumcellians,</hi> and all of
them <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> and the <hi>Circumcellians</hi> were a Generation of
Zealots, ſo fierce and impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, that <hi>Domitian</hi> himſelf did not
uſe more cruelty in ſhedding Chriſtians bloud, nor <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> who
was <hi>in Rempublicam Chriſtianam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genioſe nequam,</hi> could ever
contrive more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Inſtruments to deſtroy Chriſtianity withall,
than theſe <hi>Donatists</hi> were, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he countenanced them
againſt the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks. <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93904:36"/>And when at laſt their
grievances, and the grounds of the Schiſme came to be inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into, in the
Conference of <hi>Carthage,</hi> they could object nothing againſt the
Catholicks, but what here the Phariſees did againſt <hi>Christ, Why eateth
your Maſter with Publicans and Sinners?</hi> And can any Chriſtian Spirit
think, that this Plea for a Levitical Ceremony, will juſtifie ſuch
barbarous cruelties and bloody Sacrifices before him, who hath ſaid, <hi>I
will have Mercy and not Sacrifice?</hi> For let it be conſidered, that we
live in a Church, which is eſtabliſhed on the foundation of the Prophets
and Apoſtles, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf being the chief
corner-ſtone; a Church, wherein no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is forbidden which the Word of God
commands, nor any thing commanded, which that forbids; a Church, whoſe
Conſtitutions are truly Ancient and Apoſtolical, for which it is envied by
her Adverſaries, though bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by thoſe that ſhould be her Friends. In a
word, a Church, wherein we may be as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, devout, and charitable, as fleſh
and bloud will permit us. This Church is protected by a Gracious King, ſetled
on the Throne of his Fathers by many miracles of Providence, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to gratifie
the juſt deſires of all good Men. And what ſufficient reaſon can be
given, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the peace of ſuch a Church, or to diſobey the commands
of ſuch a King, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of peace and unity, under whom all
things are lawful, except <hi>(libertas pereundi)</hi> a licence to undo our
ſelves and others?</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:93904:36"/>
            <p>That there are ſome ſuch imperfections in the Church, as
diſcontented Perſons may quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel at, is no ſtrange thing, and if
cauſleſs and frivolous objections may be a ground for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tanta eſt imperitiae moroſitas ut vel in
rebus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batiſſimis habeat ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per quid reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat.</hi> Cal.</note>
there can never be a firm peace in any Church, ſeeing that ignorance, and
intereſt, and malice will ſtill prevail in the hearts of ſome Men: but
that ſuch things may be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and ſubmitted to, rather than to
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the foundations of peace and unity, and rent the Body of
<hi>Christ,</hi> is the judgment of all ſober Chriſtians. Our Saviour did
not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelf and his Diſciples from the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi>
Synagogues, becauſe there was a High-Prieſt, and the Scribes and
Phariſees ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair: 
<note place="margin">A tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sore is better than a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
               </note> Nor did the Apoſtle perſwade the
Chriſtians to forſake the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> wherein were many
profane Perſons, and great abuſes, but he diſſwaded them from their
diviſions, which had given occaſion to thoſe ſcandals. And if the
Church in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Maſter, do retain ſome ſinful, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in
her Communion, in hope to reform them, it is no charitable courſe to ſeduce
her Diſciples, as here the Phariſees did, <hi>Why eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth your Maſter
with Publicans and Sinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Church did impoſe ſuch Sacrifices, as the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> doth, for the Living, and the Dead; a few Pence at the
<hi>Pope</hi>'s ſhrine, for Sins paſt, preſent, and to come; if it did
require that daily Mock-ſacrifice of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Bloud of Chriſt, in the
Maſs, of which they themſelves can have no great eſteem, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93904:37"/>they order it to give place to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or
Worſhip of the Croſs, on a certain day ſet apart for that end, on which,
(ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand</hi> (<hi>Rationale l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 77.)
<hi>Horâ nonâ convenit ad adorandam crucem vacare,</hi>) they
muſt be wholly intent upon the Worſhipping of the Croſs, as if that were
indeed the Altar that did Sanctifie the Sacrifice; or if they did impoſe
ſuch gaudy and numerous Ceremonies as ſhould quite hide and obſcure the
ſubſtance of Worſhip and Devotion, that it might be ſaid of the Church
as the Poet ſays of his gaudy Girl—<hi>Pars minima eſt ipſa puella
ſui;</hi> Then we might have cauſe not only to recede, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt,
as the Martyrs did: but to contend as <hi>Hugh Broughton,</hi> and Mr.
<hi>Ainſworth</hi> did, to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and enmity upon a needleſs
controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, whether <hi>Aarons</hi> Ephod were of a Blew colour, or
Sea-water-green, and <hi>Tragoedias agere in nugis,</hi> to act Tragedies upon
no other ground than our own fears or jealouſies, and to uſe our
Chriſtian Brethren, as the Heathen did their Predeceſſors, wrap them up
in the skins of Wolves or Bears by defaming, ſlandering and condemning them,
as Profane and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian perſons, and then bait and devour them; this
is to deal worſe with them than the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did with
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe there were a better Government and diſcipline revealed
than ever yet was known, or practiſed in the Church; ſuppoſe the
Presbytery were agreeable to the pattern in the Mount, as ſome phraſe it,
(and if they had <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93904:37"/>ſaid to the pattern of the air, it had
been alike intelligible) yet if it could not be erected without Rebellion and
Rapine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the effuſion of Chriſtian bloud, and raſing the
foundations of Churches and Kingdoms, that were well eſtabliſhed in the
truth, and peace of Chriſt, the Text doth warrant the rejection of it, <hi>I
will have mercy and not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But wherein, I pray, doth the Diſcipline oppoſed by
<hi>Presbyterians, &amp;c.</hi> to the Peace and Unity of the Church, exceed or
parallel that which is already eſtabliſhed? or is it as venerable for
antiquity as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were? is there any thing of
ſuch beauty as the Temple, and the ſeveral Orders of the Prieſthood? is
it ſuch a prop to the Royal Tribe as the Prieſthood was, or doth it ſerve
the Ends of Religion, as the Sacrifices did? Alas very little of all this will
appear, it is but an invention of yeſterday, that like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s gourd
ſprung up in a night, and hath a worm alwayes gnawing at the root, and yet
men think they do well to be angry, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for it, even to the death
of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>Hath not God ſaid I hate robbery though it be for
burnt-offerings? will God be well-pleaſed with ſuch as ſacrifice their
Loyalty and Charity, and all moral virtues, to a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reformation of
Ceremonies? This Mask is ſo worn out that a <hi>Phariſee</hi> would be
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of it, and yet a late Gentleman hath <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93904:38"/>taken it
up, and though his buſineſs was to caſt fire into the ſeveral parts of
the Nation, eſpecially into the Churches, yet makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very merry,
and tells us in his Rehearſal, that the good Old Cauſe was (not only good
enough but) too good to be fought for: but God forbid, that others ſhould be
of his mind, to think only ſo well of it, as to fight for it again, for it is
ſo impoſſible, that any Cauſe fought for with ſuch horrid
circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as that was, ſhould be good, that if an Angel from Heaven, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.</note> (much leſs when only
one transformed into an Angel of light.) ſhould aſſert it, I have warrant
enough not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him.</p>
            <p>The Sacrifices and Diſcipline of the Law were termed by the
Apoſtle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7. the miniſtration of
death, becauſe without ſhedding of bloud (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) there was
no remiſſion. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.22.</note> And if in this, the
Diſcipline contended for do reſemble the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sacrifices, in
the ſhedding the bloud, not of Beaſts, but of Chriſtians, and cutting and
dividing the very body of Chriſt, in fire and ſmoke, and making whole
Kingdoms burnt-offerings, we may be aſſured the God of Mercy cannot be
well-pleaſed with ſuch Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices.</p>
            <p>The Honour of God, the Succeſs of the Goſpel, and Salvation of
Souls, is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the erecting of ſuch a Diſcipline, nor in
contending about Ceremonies, which are not otherwiſe hurtful to thoſe great
ends, <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93904:38"/>but by our needleſs contentions about them. If we
could order our Converſations according to the Doctrine of the Church, we
need not fear of diſpleaſing God by Conforming our Devotions to the Liturgy
of the Church, for <hi>the Kingdom of God is not meat and drink, but
Righteouſneſs and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> he that in
theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of
men.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">There is no Reaſon we ſhould be thus
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and mutually branded. 
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>By.</hi> Hall <hi>in a Serm. of the
miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of Faction, p.</hi> 83.</note> This man is right (ye ſay) that
man is not right, this ſound, that rotten; and how ſo, dear Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
what for Ceremonies and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for Rotchets, or Rounds, or Squares?
Let me tell you he is right that hath a right heart to his God what Form
ſoever he is for. The Kingdom of God doth not ſtand in meats or drinks, in
ſtuffs or colours or faſhions, in noiſes or geſtures, it ſtands in
Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, in Godlineſs and Charity, in Peace and
Obedience, and if we have happily attained unto theſe, God doth not ſtand
upon trifles and niceties of indifferency, and why ſhould we? Away then with
all falſe jealouſies and uncharitable gloſſes of each others actions
and eſtates. Let us all in the fear of God be intreated in the bowels of our
Dear Redeemer, as we Love our Selves, our Land, our Church, the Goſpel, to
combine our counſels and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to the holding of the Unity of the
Spirit in the bond of peace, and labour and <pb n="46" facs="tcp:93904:39"/>ſtudy, not
how to widen, and gall, and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, but how to ſalve and heal theſe
unhappy ſores of the Church and State.</q> And as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>
ſaith, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt. ad Catech. Genev.</hi>
               </note> When
we ſhall come to that great Tribunal, where we are to render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of
our Miniſtery, There ſhall be no queſtion concerning Ceremonies, neither
ſhall this conformity in outward things be brought to examination, but the
lawful uſe of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and that ſhall be adjudged lawful that
conduceth moſt to edification. Let therefore all our care, circumſpection
and diligence tend to this, which we may know ſo far to ſucceed, as we
become Proficients in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fear of God, in ſincere piety, and
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Sanctity of manners.</p>
            <p>I know you will all joyn with me, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe pitiful
pretences which are ſtill to be heard from the mouths of ſome profane
perſons, to excuſe their not frequenting of the Lords Supper, a Sacrament
which may aſſure them of infinite comfort, and bleſſings, if they did
not <hi>obicem ponere,</hi> make themſelves uncapable. They pretend a grudge
againſt a neighbour, on a <hi>punctilio</hi> of profit or reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or
perhaps a pet againſt their Miniſter, for demanding his Dues, or reproving
their Vices, and therefore they cannot come. It is the very ſame that is
pleaded againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church, in whoſe Peace and Communion
they might have Peace and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; they have ſome perverſe Opinions of
their Brethren, or Miniſter, ſome point of <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93904:39"/>Reputation,
profit, or trade lies in the way, or ſome ſtrange reports have been
whiſpered in their ears, by Schiſmatical perſons, the truth whereof they
had never time to examine, nor diſcretion to judge of; and yet there are
ſuch invincible prejudices created within them, that they cannot be
reconciled, <hi>Non amo te, nec poſſum dicere quare,</hi> that is they
muſt keep at a diſtance, and live in hatred and malice, though they have no
reaſon for it. But when God ſhall call us to an account for our ignorance,
and uncharitableneſs, and make inquiſition for the Authors and grounds of
all thoſe diviſions, that obſtinacy and cruelty that hath been
practiſed among us, what ſhall we anſwer him? can we ſay as
<hi>Saul</hi> did except it be falſly, I have kept the Commandments of the
Lord? it will be replyed then, what mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the lowing of the Oxen, and the
bleating of the Sheep that are gone aſtray? if it be pretended that they are
ſet a-part for a more ſolemn Sacrifice, the Prophet demands, hath the Lord
as great delight in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and burnt-offerings, as in obeying the Voice of
the Lord? <hi>Behold to obey</hi> (the Commands of God for Peace and Charity)
<hi>is better than Sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of Rams.</hi> Shall
we ſay all our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions were occaſioned by miſinformation, that the
Cauſe of God and the Kingdom of Chriſt were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, or that it was done
in oppoſition to a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, becauſe we would not receive the Sacrament on
our Knees, or ſee our Miniſter wear a Surplice, or becauſe we would not
ſubmit to the injunctions of our Rulers in matters of Decency, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ad ſummum illud Tribunal ventum
fuerit ubi reddenda erit olim functionis noſtrae ratio, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima erit de
Ceremoniis quaeſtio.</hi> Cal. Epiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Catech. Genev.</note> or
which is as much as any of the reſt, becauſe we would not eat with
<hi>Publicans</hi> and <pb n="48" facs="tcp:93904:40"/>ſinners? Conſider, if this be
not contrary to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours rule, of preferring Mercy above Sacrifice, when
we ſacrifice Mercy and Peace, and Charity, which are ſo ſtrictly
commanded, to our own ignorance or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, or to the diſcontent and
maliciouſneſs of wicked men, which are ſo peremptorily forbidden.</p>
            <p>Remember the Bleſſing pronounced to the Peace-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers by our
Saviour, and the Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe
againſt them that are Contentious, and obey not the Goſpel, and then think,
whether true Comfort and Piety, do lye moſt in being inſtruments of Peace, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deterior eſt qui recedit ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae
concordiâ, &amp; in haereſin aut Schiſma demigrat, quam qui
impurè vivit ſalvis dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus.</hi> Eral. de Eccl. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiâ,
p. 113.</note> of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and good Works, or in being Fire-brands in the Church
of God, inſtruments of Satan, accuſers of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, enemies of Peace,
and authors of Confuſion. And think often, that God hath made our following
of Peace, a condition of Salvation, as well as of Holineſs. <hi>Follow peace
with all men,</hi> (with all our Chriſtian Brethren more eſpecially)
<hi>without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Plea of <hi>Templum Domini,</hi> will but ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the guilt
of ſuch as do ſteal, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.4.</note> and murther, and
commit Adultery, and ſwear falſly, <hi>Is this Houſe which is called by
my Name become a den of Robbens?</hi> What greater diſhonour can we do the
Church of God than under pretence of Zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of things
inconſiderable and doubtful, to open a gap for the greateſt impiety, ſuch
as Rebellion, and Schiſm, a contempt of things Sacred and Civil, which have
been after mature deliberation and Primitive cuſtom legally eſtabliſhed
in the Church of God?</p>
            <p>If men do indeed deſire the honour and ſafety of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, 
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93904:40"/>and the whole Nation, there is no better method of
effecting it, than by a hearty endeavour, that we may all ſpeak, and mind the
ſame things, and <hi>keep the unity of the ſpirit, in the bond of
peace:</hi> by this the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs will appear, as well as the form
of it, when that Dove-like ſpirit ſhall poſſeſs our Souls, and
baniſh all thoſe proud and wrathful diſpoſitions, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>James</hi> 1.20.</note> that do as much
hinder the righteouſneſs of God, as love and charity to our Brethren. What
an honour is it to be a Repairer of the breaches of <hi>Sion,</hi> to ſettle
the Ark of God, that hath been ſo long in a wandring condition, to convert
Thouſands of Souls from the error of their ways, and as the good
<hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> pour in Wine and Oyl to their wounds, that have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
among Thieves, in their journeying from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to
<hi>Jericho?</hi> If <hi>Christ</hi> will ſo graciouſly reward at the
laſt day, all thoſe temporal and bodily ſupplies, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on
his diſtreſſed Members, as himſelf hath expreſſed, <hi>Matth.</hi>
25.34. much more bountifully will he recompenſe all that labour of love,
which we manifeſt for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of thoſe Souls, which he redeemed
with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud, to reduce a ſinner from the error of his ways, by a
mild reproof, a ſeaſonable inſtruction, a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and pious example.
This is to be as <hi>Moſes</hi> was to <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> (<hi>Exod.</hi>
4.16.) inſtead of a God and a Saviour unto them. Great is the advantage and
opportunity that thoſe Men have, who by their parts and reputation have an
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the ſpirits and conſciences of their miſguid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Brethren,
if they would inſtruct them in this plain leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of preferring works of
mercy and charity above all external ſervices whatſoever; if they would
convince them, how hateful to God a Phariſaical temper is, that diſpoſeth
Men to quarrel about external circumſtances, <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93904:41"/>wherein they
are not at all concerned, and to neglect the moſt neceſſary duties of the
Goſpel, Judgment, Mercy, and Faith, which are of Eternal concernment to their
Souls. In ſo doing, they may ſave themſelves, and perhaps thouſands of
thoſe that know them, and are ready to follow them. And if there be a
pleaſure in doing good, there is no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure like that, which will
ariſe, from being inſtrumental in ſo publick a bleſſing, wherein the
very being of Religion, the peace of the Nation, &amp; the ſalvation of
ſouls are bound together, eſpecially in this juncture of affairs, when for
want of exerciſing mercy to one another, we expoſe our ſelves as a
Sacrifice to our common enemies. <hi>Miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam volo,</hi> is God's voice
to us, and may it ever be heard in our Land. If he ſhould have dealt with us,
as we do one with another, &amp; lay hold of every provocation to deſtroy us,
the whole Land might have been a ſacrifice to his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: but <hi>he hath
in the midſt of judgment remembred mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and ſeeing it is his mercy
that we are not conſumed, let us not be ſo unmerciful to our ſelves, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.15.</note> as to bite &amp;
devour one another till we be utterly conſumed. <hi>Miſericordiam
volo,</hi> is the Kings Motto, as well as God's; He hath ſometime
graciouſly manifeſted his readineſs, to diſpenſe with the uſe of
thoſe eſtabliſhed forms of worſhip, which himſelf retains as moſt
agreeable to the Word of God, and in which, the Arguments and Sufferings of his
Royal Father have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed him (next to a <hi>Jus Divinum</hi>) againſt all
doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or contradictions: yet to ſhew that he alſo loves mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, rather
than ſacrifice, he indulged the omiſſion of them, as long as the peace
and welfare of the Nation could bear it; how ill do they requite this great
condeſcenſion, that will not recede one ſtep from their pretended holy,
but really unpeaceable Diſcipline, to follow ſuch a Divine and 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93904:41"/>Royal example, as both God and the King do propoſe to
them? <hi>Miſericordiam volo,</hi> ſhould be our Petition to the King to
pardon all that obſtinacy and peeviſhneſs of ſpirit, that keeps us
ſtill in diſobedience and contradiction to thoſe good and wholeſome
Laws, whereby we might <hi>lead quiet and peaceable lives, in all godlineſs
and honesty,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.2. Sure I am <hi>Miſericordiam volo</hi> will one
day be our Petition to God, that he would not enter into judgment with us; and
we may know what our ſentence will be then, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16.</note> for by the Goſpel
we muſt be judged, and that aſſures us that <hi>with what judgment we
judge we ſhall be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and, 
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.2.</note> 
               <hi>he ſhall have judgment
without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that ſheweth no mercy,</hi> James 2.13. <hi>Voluit Deus ut
quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſit ſibi menſura miſericordiae.</hi> And now
<hi>Miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam volo,</hi> ſhall be my Plea alſo, that you would
pardon my treſpaſſing on your patience, and that you would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a
word of Exhortation. God hath planted us in his own Vineyard, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 5.</note> hedged us about with
his Almighty providence, and been at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Miracles of Mercy, to
reſtore and eſtabliſh us on foundations of peace and righteouſneſs:
And now that he expects Grapes, <hi>let us not bring forth wild grapes,</hi> he
looketh for judgment, <hi>let us not bring forth oppreſſion,</hi> and when
he expects righteouſneſs, let us not bring forth a cry of our own ſins
and diviſions, and the ſufferings of our brethren, leſt he take away our
hedge, and we be eaten up, and leſt he break down our wall, and we be trodden
down of them, that bear evil will to <hi>Sion,</hi> and watch opportunities to
lay us waſt.</p>
            <p>If there be any fanatick principle among us, (and there are
certainly very many) this is one, to think that purity of Ordinances will
commute for the impurity of our <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93904:42"/>lives, or that we are
either better, or ſafer, for being of this, or that Party: <hi>Lot</hi> and
<hi>Noah</hi> are commended for being righteous in a wicked, and perverſe
Generation; their condemnation will be the greater, that are wicked and
unrighteous in a holy Nation, and Schiſmatical in the Communion of a Church
truly Catholick and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal: Let none of us be as the Sons of
<hi>Eli,</hi> Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> that ſnatched at the fleſh while it
was raw, and ſerved themſelves before the Lord, whereby they made the
of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of the Lord to be abhorred of the People: Let none of us be like the
Proud and Hypocritical Phariſees, who thought to cloke their real impieties,
in neglecting works of mercy and peace, by a pretence of zeal for the minute
circumſtances of external Worſhip and Diſciplin; but let us offer to God
the ſacrifices of a humble and contrite heart, and not forget <hi>to do good,
and communicate, 
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.16.</note> for with ſuch ſacrifices
God is well pleaſed:</hi> and then he will accept our praiſes, and anſwer
our Prayers with a <hi>Miſericordiam volo: I will have mercy upon you, and
heal your Land.</hi> Which God grant for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt,
<hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93904:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
